<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-14T10:39:20+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Insights from the Experienced</title><subtitle>I am a software engineering professional, writes about engineering, food and economics.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Beyond the Classroom: How student tech programs shaped my journey</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/beyond-the-classroom-how-student-tech-programs-shaped-my-journey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond the Classroom: How student tech programs shaped my journey" /><published>2024-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/beyond-the-classroom-how-student-tech-programs-shaped-my-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/beyond-the-classroom-how-student-tech-programs-shaped-my-journey.html"><![CDATA[<p>As a curious individual, my journey in technology began in the 2010s thanks to student technology programs. Programs like Microsoft Student Partner, Github Education Program, and Google Student Ambassador were eye-opening experiences for me and my peers. During my time pursuing a Bachelor’s in Computer Science and Engineering at Anna University, through M. Kumarasamy College of Engineering in Karur, I had the freedom to engage in various tech programs and communities. This journey led me to inaugurate and build tech communities within the college.</p><p>My involvement in multiple technology communities, starting with the Microsoft Student Program and the Google Developers Group Chapter in Coimbatore, introduced me to the world of open source and cloud engineering. I had opportunities to learn, experiment, build, and educate others on modern tech stacks. These experiences opened doors to internships at various organisations and participation in events organised by companies like Microsoft, Google, Tata Consultancy Services, Wipro, Dell, and others.</p><figure><img alt="A narrow, serene street in Stockholm with historic buildings and a distant church dome framed by autumn trees." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*03GPRq_YHAIppv0lbZHtWQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>A narrow, serene street in Stockholm with historic buildings and a distant church dome framed by autumn trees.</figcaption></figure><h4><strong>Through my active participation in technical associations and communities, I gained valuable hard and soft skills. </strong>Some of the most important lessons learned include,</h4><p><strong>Communication and Collaboration:</strong> Community involvement necessitates active participation in diverse activities. This includes marketing events, organising tech fests, coordinating with volunteers to conduct workshops and community-driven events, advocating for technology and tech-led products, securing sponsorships, and engaging in speaking opportunities at various forums and hackathons. Effective communication is crucial for clearly conveying ideas and ensuring successful execution. The collaboration further enhances workflows and outcomes.</p><p><strong>Decision Making:</strong> Every piece of information received or created presents an opportunity for decision-making. In tech communities, decisions are made daily, ranging from event planning, securing sponsorships, and successfully executing events to gathering feedback and making improvements.</p><p><strong>Delivering Value:</strong> The transformative nature of the tech industry requires communities to stay abreast of the latest releases and manage change effectively. This experience taught me valuable lessons in change management, future planning, risk mitigation, navigating challenges, and continuously updating my skills to achieve success.</p><p><strong>Program and Project Management:</strong> Being part of a community extends beyond simply delivering value; it involves learning about program management and tackling real-life problems to maintain momentum and inspire fellow students to participate in the tech world and foster innovation. This provided opportunities to learn project management using tools like Jira, Confluence for documentation, Trello, and Notion, all of which offer free versions for students.</p><figure><img alt="A crowd gathers beneath the famous Prague Astronomical Clock on a clear day, admiring the intricate details of the historic tower." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*BVU92xC2LMY_NRsUmn9hsQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>A crowd gathers beneath the famous Prague Astronomical Clock on a clear day, admiring the intricate details of the historic tower.</figcaption></figure><p><strong>Delegation:</strong> Understanding the nature of work and prioritising tasks based on importance and time sensitivity are essential for achieving optimal outcomes. Delegating tasks to fellow community members allows for skill development while enabling focus on critical tasks and enhancing overall productivity.</p><p><strong>Leadership:</strong> Effectively managing and leading communities requires strong leadership skills. A leader inspires fellow members through their work ethic and indirectly influences them to adopt their approach. Key leadership qualities include empathy, honest feedback, mentorship, leading by example, and providing support for task completion.</p><p><strong>Technology Toolbox:</strong> Like a mechanic’s toolbox, a technology toolbox is essential for success. This toolbox should include productivity tools, such as Microsoft Office or Google Workspace, as well as project and product management tools. Essential development tools include, but are not limited to, programming languages like Java, Python, React, JS, and other relevant frameworks. Low-code and no-code tools for business enthusiasts, design and graphics engineering tools for designers, testing tools for testing engineers, network and security tools, and cloud and AI technologies are also crucial for success.</p><h4>Technology companies often recognise the potential of the future workforce and offer free licenses and tools for students to build, test, and experiment with their products and services.</h4><h4>Some of them are listed below, research on this topic to get more benefits.</h4><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/education">GitHub Education</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/kamath/student-free-stuff">GitHub - kamath/student-free-stuff: Just a list of free software dev tools students can get</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/AchoArnold/discount-for-student-dev">GitHub - AchoArnold/discount-for-student-dev: This is list of discounts on software (SaaS, PaaS, IaaS, etc.) and other offerings for developers who are students</a></li></ul><p>These lessons learned from being a part of student tech communities have been invaluable in shaping my career and personal growth. I encourage all aspiring technologists to actively engage in these communities to foster their development and contribute to the ever-evolving world of technology.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=d6b3e604dae6" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="engineering-students" /><category term="microsoft-student-partner" /><category term="student-societies" /><category term="google-developer-group" /><category term="technology-community" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a curious individual, my journey in technology began in the 2010s thanks to student technology programs. Programs like Microsoft Student Partner, Github Education Program, and Google Student Ambassador were eye-opening experiences for me and my peers. During my time pursuing a Bachelor’s in Computer Science and Engineering at Anna University, through M. Kumarasamy College of Engineering in Karur, I had the freedom to engage in various tech programs and communities. This journey led me to inaugurate and build tech communities within the college.My involvement in multiple technology communities, starting with the Microsoft Student Program and the Google Developers Group Chapter in Coimbatore, introduced me to the world of open source and cloud engineering. I had opportunities to learn, experiment, build, and educate others on modern tech stacks. These experiences opened doors to internships at various organisations and participation in events organised by companies like Microsoft, Google, Tata Consultancy Services, Wipro, Dell, and others.A narrow, serene street in Stockholm with historic buildings and a distant church dome framed by autumn trees.Through my active participation in technical associations and communities, I gained valuable hard and soft skills. Some of the most important lessons learned include,Communication and Collaboration: Community involvement necessitates active participation in diverse activities. This includes marketing events, organising tech fests, coordinating with volunteers to conduct workshops and community-driven events, advocating for technology and tech-led products, securing sponsorships, and engaging in speaking opportunities at various forums and hackathons. Effective communication is crucial for clearly conveying ideas and ensuring successful execution. The collaboration further enhances workflows and outcomes.Decision Making: Every piece of information received or created presents an opportunity for decision-making. In tech communities, decisions are made daily, ranging from event planning, securing sponsorships, and successfully executing events to gathering feedback and making improvements.Delivering Value: The transformative nature of the tech industry requires communities to stay abreast of the latest releases and manage change effectively. This experience taught me valuable lessons in change management, future planning, risk mitigation, navigating challenges, and continuously updating my skills to achieve success.Program and Project Management: Being part of a community extends beyond simply delivering value; it involves learning about program management and tackling real-life problems to maintain momentum and inspire fellow students to participate in the tech world and foster innovation. This provided opportunities to learn project management using tools like Jira, Confluence for documentation, Trello, and Notion, all of which offer free versions for students.A crowd gathers beneath the famous Prague Astronomical Clock on a clear day, admiring the intricate details of the historic tower.Delegation: Understanding the nature of work and prioritising tasks based on importance and time sensitivity are essential for achieving optimal outcomes. Delegating tasks to fellow community members allows for skill development while enabling focus on critical tasks and enhancing overall productivity.Leadership: Effectively managing and leading communities requires strong leadership skills. A leader inspires fellow members through their work ethic and indirectly influences them to adopt their approach. Key leadership qualities include empathy, honest feedback, mentorship, leading by example, and providing support for task completion.Technology Toolbox: Like a mechanic’s toolbox, a technology toolbox is essential for success. This toolbox should include productivity tools, such as Microsoft Office or Google Workspace, as well as project and product management tools. Essential development tools include, but are not limited to, programming languages like Java, Python, React, JS, and other relevant frameworks. Low-code and no-code tools for business enthusiasts, design and graphics engineering tools for designers, testing tools for testing engineers, network and security tools, and cloud and AI technologies are also crucial for success.Technology companies often recognise the potential of the future workforce and offer free licenses and tools for students to build, test, and experiment with their products and services.Some of them are listed below, research on this topic to get more benefits.GitHub EducationGitHub - kamath/student-free-stuff: Just a list of free software dev tools students can getGitHub - AchoArnold/discount-for-student-dev: This is list of discounts on software (SaaS, PaaS, IaaS, etc.) and other offerings for developers who are studentsThese lessons learned from being a part of student tech communities have been invaluable in shaping my career and personal growth. I encourage all aspiring technologists to actively engage in these communities to foster their development and contribute to the ever-evolving world of technology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Investing in Customer Reliability: Why it matters for Cloud Providers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/27/investing-in-customer-reliability-why-it-matters-for-cloud-providers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investing in Customer Reliability: Why it matters for Cloud Providers" /><published>2024-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/27/investing-in-customer-reliability-why-it-matters-for-cloud-providers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/27/investing-in-customer-reliability-why-it-matters-for-cloud-providers.html"><![CDATA[<p>In today’s digital landscape, reliability is paramount, especially for businesses reliant on cloud services. Cloud providers like Google Cloud understand this and are increasingly investing in <strong>Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE)</strong>. But what’s in it for them? Why empower customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability? Let’s explore the compelling reasons behind this trend.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*b4O92EM8pcC-2jNaTw48rA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Two people in cosy sweaters serve “Varm Glögg” from a festive, snow-topped wooden stall at a Christmas market in Stockholm, illuminated by warm lights.</figcaption></figure><h4>Time to learn about Glögg 🍷</h4><p>Glögg is a Swedish word, that refers to the traditional Scandinavian mulled wine, typically served warm during the winter months and Christmas season. It’s spiced with cinnamon, cloves, cardamom, and often served with almonds and raisins, offering a cosy, festive flavour.</p><p>Shifting our focus back, cloud providers are investing in customer reliability engineering for the following reasons</p><h4><strong>Reliability breeds trust and loyalty</strong></h4><p>For cloud vendors, a reliable service is the bedrock of customer trust. When businesses entrust their critical operations to a cloud provider, they expect consistent uptime and minimal disruptions. By investing in CRE and providing customers with the tools and knowledge to manage their own reliability, cloud vendors foster a sense of partnership and confidence. This, in turn, translates to increased customer loyalty and long-term relationships.</p><h4><strong>Shared responsibility, shared success</strong></h4><p>Cloud computing thrives on a shared responsibility model. While providers are responsible for the underlying infrastructure, customers play a crucial role in building and managing reliable applications on top of that infrastructure. By empowering customers with CRE principles and practices, cloud vendors enable them to take ownership of their reliability, leading to a more stable and successful ecosystem for all involved.</p><h4><strong>Reducing downtime costs</strong></h4><p>Downtime can be incredibly expensive for businesses, leading to lost revenue, damaged reputation, and recovery efforts. By proactively addressing reliability concerns and equipping customers to manage their systems effectively, cloud vendors contribute to minimising potential downtime risks. This proactive approach reduces the likelihood of costly outages for both the customer and the provider.</p><h4><strong>Unlocking business value through stability</strong></h4><p>When businesses can rely on the stability of their cloud environments, they are free to innovate and focus on their core competencies. CRE empowers customers to build mission-critical teams that can ensure the smooth operation of their applications, allowing them to leverage the full potential of the cloud without being bogged down by reliability concerns</p><h4><strong>A culture of continuous improvement</strong></h4><p>Investing in CRE fosters a culture of continuous improvement within both the cloud provider and the customer’s organisation. By embracing principles like blameless postmortems and proactive monitoring, both parties can identify areas for optimisation and continuously enhance the reliability of their systems.</p><p>In conclusion, cloud providers are investing in <strong>Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE)</strong> because it’s a strategic imperative in today’s competitive market. By empowering customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability, they’re not just selling services, they’re building long-term partnerships based on trust, shared success, and a commitment to delivering exceptional digital experiences.</p><h4>Reference:</h4><p><a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/devops-sre/introducing-a-new-era-of-customer-support-google-customer-reliability-engineering">Introducing Google Customer Reliability Engineering | Google Cloud Blog</a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=30d23c1fb0f7" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cloud-partnerships" /><category term="cloud-computing" /><category term="customer-experience" /><category term="reliability-engineering" /><category term="google-cloud-platform" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In today’s digital landscape, reliability is paramount, especially for businesses reliant on cloud services. Cloud providers like Google Cloud understand this and are increasingly investing in Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE). But what’s in it for them? Why empower customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability? Let’s explore the compelling reasons behind this trend.Two people in cosy sweaters serve “Varm Glögg” from a festive, snow-topped wooden stall at a Christmas market in Stockholm, illuminated by warm lights.Time to learn about Glögg 🍷Glögg is a Swedish word, that refers to the traditional Scandinavian mulled wine, typically served warm during the winter months and Christmas season. It’s spiced with cinnamon, cloves, cardamom, and often served with almonds and raisins, offering a cosy, festive flavour.Shifting our focus back, cloud providers are investing in customer reliability engineering for the following reasonsReliability breeds trust and loyaltyFor cloud vendors, a reliable service is the bedrock of customer trust. When businesses entrust their critical operations to a cloud provider, they expect consistent uptime and minimal disruptions. By investing in CRE and providing customers with the tools and knowledge to manage their own reliability, cloud vendors foster a sense of partnership and confidence. This, in turn, translates to increased customer loyalty and long-term relationships.Shared responsibility, shared successCloud computing thrives on a shared responsibility model. While providers are responsible for the underlying infrastructure, customers play a crucial role in building and managing reliable applications on top of that infrastructure. By empowering customers with CRE principles and practices, cloud vendors enable them to take ownership of their reliability, leading to a more stable and successful ecosystem for all involved.Reducing downtime costsDowntime can be incredibly expensive for businesses, leading to lost revenue, damaged reputation, and recovery efforts. By proactively addressing reliability concerns and equipping customers to manage their systems effectively, cloud vendors contribute to minimising potential downtime risks. This proactive approach reduces the likelihood of costly outages for both the customer and the provider.Unlocking business value through stabilityWhen businesses can rely on the stability of their cloud environments, they are free to innovate and focus on their core competencies. CRE empowers customers to build mission-critical teams that can ensure the smooth operation of their applications, allowing them to leverage the full potential of the cloud without being bogged down by reliability concernsA culture of continuous improvementInvesting in CRE fosters a culture of continuous improvement within both the cloud provider and the customer’s organisation. By embracing principles like blameless postmortems and proactive monitoring, both parties can identify areas for optimisation and continuously enhance the reliability of their systems.In conclusion, cloud providers are investing in Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE) because it’s a strategic imperative in today’s competitive market. By empowering customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability, they’re not just selling services, they’re building long-term partnerships based on trust, shared success, and a commitment to delivering exceptional digital experiences.Reference:Introducing Google Customer Reliability Engineering | Google Cloud Blog]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google’s Gemini at Work: Data is the key</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/26/google-s-gemini-at-work-data-is-the-key.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google’s Gemini at Work: Data is the key" /><published>2024-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/26/google-s-gemini-at-work-data-is-the-key</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/26/google-s-gemini-at-work-data-is-the-key.html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday’s “Gemini at Work Live” event showcased Google’s latest AI advancements, emphasizing how <strong>data is crucial for unlocking AI’s potential</strong>. While “foundation models” are powerful, the event stressed that they alone aren’t enough. Businesses need a holistic strategy to prepare data, choose the right models, and seamlessly integrate them into their systems. This is where Google’s offerings shine.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*j2n3NOmkwgVkUQTKTjEDig.png" /><figcaption>Statue of Birger Jarl at Riddarholmen in Stockholm</figcaption></figure><h3>Gemini: More Than Just Models</h3><p>The event highlighted Gemini’s capabilities beyond basic AI models. Here are some key takeaways:</p><p><strong>Customer-Centric Solutions:</strong> Gemini is revolutionising customer service with intelligent agents. Imagine agents that not only understand complex requests but also provide personalised experiences.</p><p><strong>Boosting Workplace Efficiency:</strong> Gemini is set to redefine productivity. Employee agents will streamline tasks, offer instant information access, and make workflows incredibly smooth.</p><p><strong>Data at Your Fingertips:</strong> Features like Vertex AI Search, powered by Google’s renowned search technology, will allow businesses to extract invaluable insights from their data.</p><p><strong>Looker Gets Smarter:</strong> With Gemini, Looker becomes even more powerful. Conversational analytics allows users to interact with data using natural language, get AI-driven suggestions, and visualise insights effortlessly.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FqmIZyPJgRiI%3Ffeature%3Doembed&amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DqmIZyPJgRiI&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FqmIZyPJgRiI%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/efd9b486dddfa7bc46098b4925b80f2c/href">https://medium.com/media/efd9b486dddfa7bc46098b4925b80f2c/href</a></iframe><h3>BigQuery: The Data Powerhouse</h3><p>The event positioned BigQuery as the cornerstone of this AI revolution. Here’s why:</p><p><strong>Unified Engine:</strong> BigQuery’s new unified engine ensures high performance and seamless management, making it ideal for handling the demands of AI workloads.</p><p><strong>Unified Storage:</strong> BigQuery is designed to handle various data types (multimodal data), a crucial aspect of today’s diverse data landscape.</p><p><strong>Built-in AI:</strong> With BigQuery ML and other integration capabilities, BigQuery emerges as a comprehensive platform for AI solutions.</p><h3>Finally Google’s AI Advantage</h3><p>The event strongly emphasized Google Cloud’s unified tech stack as a significant advantage.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*WAn3EVhBqnxdQevBOW0WDw.png" /><figcaption>Google Cloud’s AI Optimised Stack</figcaption></figure><p><strong>AI Hypercomputer:</strong> This forms the foundation for Google’s AI prowess.</p><p><strong>Vertex AI:</strong> This serves as the platform for building and deploying AI models, including the powerful Model Garden.</p><p><strong>Gemini:</strong> This sits at the forefront, powering Google Cloud, Workspace, and specialised Agents.</p><p>The event presented a compelling case for businesses to view their data as a competitive advantage in the age of AI. Google Cloud, with its suite of integrated solutions like Gemini, Vertex AI, and BigQuery, offers a comprehensive pathway for businesses to harness their data’s full potential.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=8faf31a93774" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="google-cloud-platform" /><category term="vertex-ai" /><category term="bigquery" /><category term="google-gemini" /><category term="google-ai" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday’s “Gemini at Work Live” event showcased Google’s latest AI advancements, emphasizing how data is crucial for unlocking AI’s potential. While “foundation models” are powerful, the event stressed that they alone aren’t enough. Businesses need a holistic strategy to prepare data, choose the right models, and seamlessly integrate them into their systems. This is where Google’s offerings shine.Statue of Birger Jarl at Riddarholmen in StockholmGemini: More Than Just ModelsThe event highlighted Gemini’s capabilities beyond basic AI models. Here are some key takeaways:Customer-Centric Solutions: Gemini is revolutionising customer service with intelligent agents. Imagine agents that not only understand complex requests but also provide personalised experiences.Boosting Workplace Efficiency: Gemini is set to redefine productivity. Employee agents will streamline tasks, offer instant information access, and make workflows incredibly smooth.Data at Your Fingertips: Features like Vertex AI Search, powered by Google’s renowned search technology, will allow businesses to extract invaluable insights from their data.Looker Gets Smarter: With Gemini, Looker becomes even more powerful. Conversational analytics allows users to interact with data using natural language, get AI-driven suggestions, and visualise insights effortlessly.https://medium.com/media/efd9b486dddfa7bc46098b4925b80f2c/hrefBigQuery: The Data PowerhouseThe event positioned BigQuery as the cornerstone of this AI revolution. Here’s why:Unified Engine: BigQuery’s new unified engine ensures high performance and seamless management, making it ideal for handling the demands of AI workloads.Unified Storage: BigQuery is designed to handle various data types (multimodal data), a crucial aspect of today’s diverse data landscape.Built-in AI: With BigQuery ML and other integration capabilities, BigQuery emerges as a comprehensive platform for AI solutions.Finally Google’s AI AdvantageThe event strongly emphasized Google Cloud’s unified tech stack as a significant advantage.Google Cloud’s AI Optimised StackAI Hypercomputer: This forms the foundation for Google’s AI prowess.Vertex AI: This serves as the platform for building and deploying AI models, including the powerful Model Garden.Gemini: This sits at the forefront, powering Google Cloud, Workspace, and specialised Agents.The event presented a compelling case for businesses to view their data as a competitive advantage in the age of AI. Google Cloud, with its suite of integrated solutions like Gemini, Vertex AI, and BigQuery, offers a comprehensive pathway for businesses to harness their data’s full potential.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI Infrastructure business is a pricey endeavor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/17/ai-infrastructure-business-is-a-pricey-endeavor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Infrastructure business is a pricey endeavor" /><published>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/17/ai-infrastructure-business-is-a-pricey-endeavor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/17/ai-infrastructure-business-is-a-pricey-endeavor.html"><![CDATA[<p>While AI might seem magical, in the business world, it’s about automating tasks using machines that learn from data and real-world situations. Advancements in Natural Language Generation (NLG) have led to Large Language Models (LLMs) and their ongoing improvement.</p><h4><strong>The hidden workhorse: AI Infrastructure</strong></h4><p>Often overlooked is the crucial role of AI engineering. It involves managing the data that fuels AI models and ensures they deliver the expected results when prompted. Handling this data at scale requires a robust infrastructure for both data and AI engineering workloads. Imagine an iceberg; the visible tip represents the AI system, while the vast, hidden part is the supporting infrastructure.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*ClyDM1Ot9zsfPoUe6K_rlQ.png" /><figcaption>Iceberg and the AI Systems</figcaption></figure><p>It’s exciting to see how your hand-drawn iceberg floats in real life. Thanks to Sketchplanations for introducing me to Iceberger, where you can create your iceberg and watch it float. Give it a try and be a kid again!</p><p><a href="https://joshdata.me/iceberger.html">Iceberger</a></p><h4>Why starting an AI Infrastructure company now might be tough</h4><p>This section doesn’t discuss the basics of building infrastructure or AI systems. However, venturing into AI infrastructure right now might not be ideal. Here’s a realistic perspective based on experiences within the AI ecosystem:</p><p><strong>Limited Market for Niche Solutions: </strong>Imagine starting a business to support a single vendor needing custom infrastructure for on-premise LLMs. This approach might not attract many future customers.</p><p><strong>Challenges in a Competitive Landscape:</strong> The existing market is competitive. Convincing customers to move away from established cloud vendors with their comprehensive governance, platforms, and tight integration is difficult.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*thvyZyIIbA4peuVSzCPIVA.jpeg" /><figcaption>The Grand Riksdag building (Sweden’s Parliament)</figcaption></figure><h4><strong>Key considerations for a successful AI Infrastructure startup</strong></h4><p>Here are some crucial aspects to consider for a future-proof AI infrastructure company:</p><ol><li><strong>Extensive research and development:</strong> Investing heavily in R&amp;D is essential to stay ahead of the curve and meet evolving customer needs.</li><li><strong>Technology stack:</strong> Innovating the right, scalable and flexible technology stack is crucial to accommodate current and future customer demands.</li><li><strong>Marketing and sales strategy:</strong> Develop a clear plan for marketing, sales communication, collaboration, and partnerships.</li><li><strong>Streamlined customer onboarding:</strong> Simplify the onboarding process, considering the fast-paced changes in the AI landscape.</li><li><strong>Predicting customer needs:</strong> Anticipate customer expectations to tailor your go-to-market strategy effectively.</li><li><strong>Focus on broader solutions:</strong> Instead of hyper-niche solutions, target broader problems affecting a wider range of customers.</li><li><strong>Understanding established players:</strong> Large companies have complex needs. A startup might not be able to solve all their problems, as changes in strategy and new product adoption can trigger internal changes and unique challenges.</li><li><strong>Cost optimization in a cloud-native world:</strong> Helping cloud-native customers find their sweet spot for cost savings and system efficiency is a significant challenge.</li><li><strong>Idea protection:</strong> While intellectual property theft is a concern, established companies can quickly adapt and implement innovative ideas.</li></ol><h4>Conclusion</h4><p>The AI infrastructure space is challenging but holds promise. Careful consideration of the market landscape and a well-defined strategy are crucial for success.</p><h4>Reference</h4><p>Iceberg Picture <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iceberg">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iceberg</a><br>Sketchplanations <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/iceberg-orientation">https://sketchplanations.com/iceberg-orientation</a><br>Iceberger <a href="https://joshdata.me/iceberger.html">https://joshdata.me/iceberger.html</a><br>Insights about AI Infrastructure startups <a href="https://nextword.substack.com/p/why-ai-infrastructure-startups-are">https://nextword.substack.com/p/why-ai-infrastructure-startups-are</a><br>Tools<a href="https://gemini.google.com/"> Google Gemini</a> for improvements and <a href="https://app.diagrams.net/">draw.io</a> for designing diagrams.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=5d2ba9812838" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-infrastructure-market" /><category term="ai-business" /><category term="ai-infrastructure" /><category term="ai" /><category term="ai-startups" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While AI might seem magical, in the business world, it’s about automating tasks using machines that learn from data and real-world situations. Advancements in Natural Language Generation (NLG) have led to Large Language Models (LLMs) and their ongoing improvement.The hidden workhorse: AI InfrastructureOften overlooked is the crucial role of AI engineering. It involves managing the data that fuels AI models and ensures they deliver the expected results when prompted. Handling this data at scale requires a robust infrastructure for both data and AI engineering workloads. Imagine an iceberg; the visible tip represents the AI system, while the vast, hidden part is the supporting infrastructure.Iceberg and the AI SystemsIt’s exciting to see how your hand-drawn iceberg floats in real life. Thanks to Sketchplanations for introducing me to Iceberger, where you can create your iceberg and watch it float. Give it a try and be a kid again!IcebergerWhy starting an AI Infrastructure company now might be toughThis section doesn’t discuss the basics of building infrastructure or AI systems. However, venturing into AI infrastructure right now might not be ideal. Here’s a realistic perspective based on experiences within the AI ecosystem:Limited Market for Niche Solutions: Imagine starting a business to support a single vendor needing custom infrastructure for on-premise LLMs. This approach might not attract many future customers.Challenges in a Competitive Landscape: The existing market is competitive. Convincing customers to move away from established cloud vendors with their comprehensive governance, platforms, and tight integration is difficult.The Grand Riksdag building (Sweden’s Parliament)Key considerations for a successful AI Infrastructure startupHere are some crucial aspects to consider for a future-proof AI infrastructure company:Extensive research and development: Investing heavily in R&amp;D is essential to stay ahead of the curve and meet evolving customer needs.Technology stack: Innovating the right, scalable and flexible technology stack is crucial to accommodate current and future customer demands.Marketing and sales strategy: Develop a clear plan for marketing, sales communication, collaboration, and partnerships.Streamlined customer onboarding: Simplify the onboarding process, considering the fast-paced changes in the AI landscape.Predicting customer needs: Anticipate customer expectations to tailor your go-to-market strategy effectively.Focus on broader solutions: Instead of hyper-niche solutions, target broader problems affecting a wider range of customers.Understanding established players: Large companies have complex needs. A startup might not be able to solve all their problems, as changes in strategy and new product adoption can trigger internal changes and unique challenges.Cost optimization in a cloud-native world: Helping cloud-native customers find their sweet spot for cost savings and system efficiency is a significant challenge.Idea protection: While intellectual property theft is a concern, established companies can quickly adapt and implement innovative ideas.ConclusionThe AI infrastructure space is challenging but holds promise. Careful consideration of the market landscape and a well-defined strategy are crucial for success.ReferenceIceberg Picture https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IcebergSketchplanations https://sketchplanations.com/iceberg-orientationIceberger https://joshdata.me/iceberger.htmlInsights about AI Infrastructure startups https://nextword.substack.com/p/why-ai-infrastructure-startups-areTools Google Gemini for improvements and draw.io for designing diagrams.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Podcast on Database Mastery: Insights from a Seasoned Engineer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/10/podcast-on-database-mastery-insights-from-a-seasoned-engineer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcast on Database Mastery: Insights from a Seasoned Engineer" /><published>2024-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/08/10/podcast-on-database-mastery-insights-from-a-seasoned-engineer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/10/podcast-on-database-mastery-insights-from-a-seasoned-engineer.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a habit of mine to share my thoughts on software engineering, real-world tech applications, and random musings on food, culture, and life experiences. Recently, I’ve dived deeper into podcasting, finding Spotify invaluable for distribution and Podcastle.ai a helpful tool for recording and post-production. I enjoy capturing insights from experienced individuals to share with others for their growth. To kick things off, I’ve collaborated with friends in the software industry to share their educational journeys, professional tips, and advice for early career professionals.</p><figure><img alt="Podcost Episode Cover Art" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*-PF8V92wJ1ZcTJuj8IiW1g.png" /><figcaption>Episode Cover Art</figcaption></figure><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fopen.spotify.com%2Fembed%2Fepisode%2F5r3EbJSUs3UwbNYRVgpg06%3Futm_source%3Doembed&amp;display_name=Spotify&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fopen.spotify.com%2Fepisode%2F5r3EbJSUs3UwbNYRVgpg06&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.scdn.co%2Fimage%2Fab67656300005f1f5e07eca04bfec1ce100a7c7c&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=spotify" width="456" height="152" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/d3730a02eda8b3f63fc43f2bda646db7/href">https://medium.com/media/d3730a02eda8b3f63fc43f2bda646db7/href</a></iframe><p>This episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.</p><p>This episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.</p><p>Packi’s LinkedIn Profile <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/packiyarajraja/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/packiyarajraja/</a></p><p>Packi boasts over a decade of experience working extensively with database and data engineering solutions, helping enterprises succeed worldwide. As a seasoned consultant for Fortune 500 companies, he excels at translating business needs into technical solutions.</p><figure><img alt="Kopparberg Cider" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*NgFPfF_LkL-e08RNkbPbhA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Kopparberg Cider</figcaption></figure><blockquote>Nothing beats the crisp refreshment of a cool cider on a warm summer day</blockquote><p>He emphasizes the importance of human collaboration, believing it’s crucial for personal growth. Success, for him, is built on trust with clients and stakeholders, leading to their satisfaction and ultimately, the company’s revenue.</p><p>He shares three pieces of advice for early career professionals:<br>1. Upgrade practical skills: Continuously enhance your abilities in programming, design, architecture, testing, analysis, etc.<br>2. Pursue your interests: Explore internships, freelancing, or open-source contributions that align with your passions.<br>3. Embrace AI: Incorporate AI into your toolkit to boost productivity.</p><p>Packi further elaborated on the impact of AI:</p><p>Before AI adoption: Highlight the traditional approach.<br>After AI adoption: Emphasize the potential for 100x productivity improvement through AI integration.</p><p>He concluded by stressing the significance of continuous learning, comparing it to fueling a car. He recommends dedicating at least 30 minutes daily to professional development.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*tkuK8GdPRgtGFSe_F8PZiA.jpeg" /><figcaption>A picture from our Yecaud trip. Lak, Packi and LP</figcaption></figure><p>I thank Packi for his time and valuable insights. And thanks LP(Lakshmipriya) for introducing Packi to me.</p><p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post.</p><p><strong>Follow my podcast channel for future episodes and your feedback is greatly appreciated.</strong></p><p><a href="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/lakshmikanth-rajamani">Insights from the Experienced * A podcast on Spotify for Podcasters</a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=4323c85bf901" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="database-engineer" /><category term="podcast" /><category term="database-development" /><category term="career-development" /><category term="career-advice" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s a habit of mine to share my thoughts on software engineering, real-world tech applications, and random musings on food, culture, and life experiences. Recently, I’ve dived deeper into podcasting, finding Spotify invaluable for distribution and Podcastle.ai a helpful tool for recording and post-production. I enjoy capturing insights from experienced individuals to share with others for their growth. To kick things off, I’ve collaborated with friends in the software industry to share their educational journeys, professional tips, and advice for early career professionals.Episode Cover Arthttps://medium.com/media/d3730a02eda8b3f63fc43f2bda646db7/hrefThis episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.This episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.Packi’s LinkedIn Profile https://www.linkedin.com/in/packiyarajraja/Packi boasts over a decade of experience working extensively with database and data engineering solutions, helping enterprises succeed worldwide. As a seasoned consultant for Fortune 500 companies, he excels at translating business needs into technical solutions.Kopparberg CiderNothing beats the crisp refreshment of a cool cider on a warm summer dayHe emphasizes the importance of human collaboration, believing it’s crucial for personal growth. Success, for him, is built on trust with clients and stakeholders, leading to their satisfaction and ultimately, the company’s revenue.He shares three pieces of advice for early career professionals:1. Upgrade practical skills: Continuously enhance your abilities in programming, design, architecture, testing, analysis, etc.2. Pursue your interests: Explore internships, freelancing, or open-source contributions that align with your passions.3. Embrace AI: Incorporate AI into your toolkit to boost productivity.Packi further elaborated on the impact of AI:Before AI adoption: Highlight the traditional approach.After AI adoption: Emphasize the potential for 100x productivity improvement through AI integration.He concluded by stressing the significance of continuous learning, comparing it to fueling a car. He recommends dedicating at least 30 minutes daily to professional development.A picture from our Yecaud trip. Lak, Packi and LPI thank Packi for his time and valuable insights. And thanks LP(Lakshmipriya) for introducing Packi to me.Thanks for taking the time to read this post.Follow my podcast channel for future episodes and your feedback is greatly appreciated.Insights from the Experienced * A podcast on Spotify for Podcasters]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Class SRE implements DevOps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/30/class-sre-implements-devops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Class SRE implements DevOps" /><published>2024-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/30/class-sre-implements-devops</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/30/class-sre-implements-devops.html"><![CDATA[<p>I am writing this blog post after taking a course from Google Cloud Boost Skills. It was fascinating to learn about the significance of SRE (Site Reliability Engineering) and DevOps in organizations of any size.</p><figure><img alt="Happy Lak is in Richmond Park, watching the deer." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*56Vs1J78eh9qhr3x435Klw.png" /><figcaption>Happy Lak is in Richmond Park, watching the deer.</figcaption></figure><p>Before diving into the importance of SRE and DevOps, let’s understand what DevOps is.</p><blockquote>Traditionally, developers and operators (the team that deploys and manages systems/applications) functioned in silos, leading to numerous challenges. This separation resulted in increased technical debt, longer time-to-market for solutions, and poor communication and collaboration between teams. Thanks to DevOps practices, teams are now structured in a more integrated manner to address both development and operational needs. This integrated approach reduces time-to-market with calculated risks, introducing terms such as SLA and SLI into the mix.</blockquote><p>SLA (Service Level Agreement): A commitment between a service provider and a client regarding the expected level of service</p><p>SLI (Service Level Indicator): A measure of the service level provided to the client</p><figure><img alt="A herd of deer is grazing in the park." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*Jp2UQNovFFZkbBaKaimUwQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>A herd of deer is grazing in the park.</figcaption></figure><p>Connecting five key touchpoints highlights the thin line between SRE and DevOps. Essentially, Class SRE implements DevOps for several reasons:</p><p>1. <strong>Reduce Organizational Silos:</strong> Siloed working environments attract numerous engineering problems. By reducing silos, organizations can bring ideas to life more optimally.</p><p>2. <strong>Accept Failure as Normal: </strong>Making mistakes is human, but learning from them is crucial. A blameless culture that performs postmortems of problems enhances the learning curve and encourages teams to take ownership.</p><p>3. <strong>Implement Gradual Change:</strong> Change is essential for growth. The technology landscape is embedded with change management at its core. Software engineering teams live by agile values, are open to changes, and consider rapid development and deployment crucial. Understanding consumer requirements, listening to feedback, and analyzing user data are vital for mutual success. Canary and blue-green deployments exemplify this approach.</p><p>4. <strong>Leverage Tools and Automation:</strong> Introducing automation empowers software engineering teams. This can range from simple tools for capturing screenshots to advanced AI companions for auto-coding. Integrating such systems into workflows boosts company productivity.</p><p>5. <strong>Measure Everything:</strong> While empowering software engineering is crucial, defining success criteria and measuring them is even more critical for business success. Defining KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) enables teams and individuals to enhance their work methods.</p><p>Stay tuned for the next post where we will dive deeper into SLA, SLI, and similar terms.</p><p>Reference:</p><p><a href="https://www.cloudskillsboost.google/course_templates/59">Site Reliability Engineering: Measuring and Managing Reliability | Google Cloud Skills Boost</a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=1c4fa0b85569" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="devops" /><category term="google-cloud-platform" /><category term="site-reliability" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am writing this blog post after taking a course from Google Cloud Boost Skills. It was fascinating to learn about the significance of SRE (Site Reliability Engineering) and DevOps in organizations of any size.Happy Lak is in Richmond Park, watching the deer.Before diving into the importance of SRE and DevOps, let’s understand what DevOps is.Traditionally, developers and operators (the team that deploys and manages systems/applications) functioned in silos, leading to numerous challenges. This separation resulted in increased technical debt, longer time-to-market for solutions, and poor communication and collaboration between teams. Thanks to DevOps practices, teams are now structured in a more integrated manner to address both development and operational needs. This integrated approach reduces time-to-market with calculated risks, introducing terms such as SLA and SLI into the mix.SLA (Service Level Agreement): A commitment between a service provider and a client regarding the expected level of serviceSLI (Service Level Indicator): A measure of the service level provided to the clientA herd of deer is grazing in the park.Connecting five key touchpoints highlights the thin line between SRE and DevOps. Essentially, Class SRE implements DevOps for several reasons:1. Reduce Organizational Silos: Siloed working environments attract numerous engineering problems. By reducing silos, organizations can bring ideas to life more optimally.2. Accept Failure as Normal: Making mistakes is human, but learning from them is crucial. A blameless culture that performs postmortems of problems enhances the learning curve and encourages teams to take ownership.3. Implement Gradual Change: Change is essential for growth. The technology landscape is embedded with change management at its core. Software engineering teams live by agile values, are open to changes, and consider rapid development and deployment crucial. Understanding consumer requirements, listening to feedback, and analyzing user data are vital for mutual success. Canary and blue-green deployments exemplify this approach.4. Leverage Tools and Automation: Introducing automation empowers software engineering teams. This can range from simple tools for capturing screenshots to advanced AI companions for auto-coding. Integrating such systems into workflows boosts company productivity.5. Measure Everything: While empowering software engineering is crucial, defining success criteria and measuring them is even more critical for business success. Defining KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) enables teams and individuals to enhance their work methods.Stay tuned for the next post where we will dive deeper into SLA, SLI, and similar terms.Reference:Site Reliability Engineering: Measuring and Managing Reliability | Google Cloud Skills Boost]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The AI Maturity Checkup: Get your organisation in shape</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/the-ai-maturity-checkup-get-your-organisation-in-shape.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The AI Maturity Checkup: Get your organisation in shape" /><published>2024-05-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/the-ai-maturity-checkup-get-your-organisation-in-shape</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/the-ai-maturity-checkup-get-your-organisation-in-shape.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*07YQ571cMyKNcjuYDBpRAA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Vaxholm in the Stockholm archipelago</figcaption></figure><blockquote><strong>AI maturity refers to the degree to which an organization has successfully integrated artificial intelligence (AI) into its operations, culture, and decision-making processes. It is a measure of how well an organization leverages AI to achieve its business goals, create value for its customers, and manage risks.</strong></blockquote><p>Key aspects of AI maturity:</p><p>1. <strong>Strategy:</strong> A clear AI strategy aligned with the organization’s goals, clearly defining use cases and their potential business impact.</p><p>2. <strong>Data:</strong> Robust data infrastructure to support AI requirements, emphasising governance, readiness, quality, privacy, and security. This ensures AI models are fueled with relevant, reliable, and responsibly handled data.</p><p>3. <strong>Technology:</strong> Careful selection of software tools and platforms that best support the computing demands of AI model development, testing, deployment, and continuous monitoring.</p><p>4. <strong>Talent:</strong> A skilled workforce comprising AI professionals, data scientists, data engineers, leaders, and subject matter experts. They are essential for driving and sustaining AI adoption.</p><p>5. <strong>Culture:</strong> A culture that fosters innovation, experimentation, and data-driven decision-making. This promotes continuous improvement for better customer outcomes. Ethical considerations and effective change management are integral to this culture.</p><p>6. <strong>Governance:</strong> Frameworks, processes, and best practices to guide the responsible and ethical development of AI solutions, ensuring alignment with legal requirements and customer interests.</p><p><strong>Levels of AI Maturity:</strong> AI maturity is often visualized as a spectrum or scale with several levels, typically ranging from</p><p>1. <strong>Nascent:</strong> Limited understanding of AI, characterized by ad-hoc experimentation.<br> <br>2. <strong>Developing:</strong> Formalization of an AI strategy begins, with initial projects underway.</p><p>3. <strong>Operational:</strong> AI is integrated into some business processes, yielding measurable results.</p><p>4. <strong>Transformative:</strong> AI is a core part of the company’s DNA, driving strategic decisions and creating significant competitive advantages.</p><p>Let’s explore AI maturity for organizational success, recognizing there’s no one-size-fits-all approach. From my experience working with Nordic enterprises, I’ve identified three key dimensions within the AI maturity diagnostic process:</p><ol><li><strong>Current State Assessment:</strong> Conduct a thorough analysis of the organization’s current AI capabilities, including infrastructure, data readiness, talent pools, and existing AI applications.</li><li><strong>Maturity Benchmarking:</strong> Compare the organization’s AI maturity with industry standards and identify areas for improvement.</li><li><strong>Gap Analysis and Recommendations:</strong> Provide detailed recommendations and a roadmap for achieving higher AI maturity.</li></ol><p>In our upcoming articles, we’ll explore the power of current state assessments, the importance of benchmarking in the AI race, and how to learn from leading AI-first companies to identify and overcome challenges quickly.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=0f1da8062bb8" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-transformation" /><category term="ai-consulting" /><category term="ai-maturity" /><category term="ai-strategy" /><category term="ai-readiness" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vaxholm in the Stockholm archipelagoAI maturity refers to the degree to which an organization has successfully integrated artificial intelligence (AI) into its operations, culture, and decision-making processes. It is a measure of how well an organization leverages AI to achieve its business goals, create value for its customers, and manage risks.Key aspects of AI maturity:1. Strategy: A clear AI strategy aligned with the organization’s goals, clearly defining use cases and their potential business impact.2. Data: Robust data infrastructure to support AI requirements, emphasising governance, readiness, quality, privacy, and security. This ensures AI models are fueled with relevant, reliable, and responsibly handled data.3. Technology: Careful selection of software tools and platforms that best support the computing demands of AI model development, testing, deployment, and continuous monitoring.4. Talent: A skilled workforce comprising AI professionals, data scientists, data engineers, leaders, and subject matter experts. They are essential for driving and sustaining AI adoption.5. Culture: A culture that fosters innovation, experimentation, and data-driven decision-making. This promotes continuous improvement for better customer outcomes. Ethical considerations and effective change management are integral to this culture.6. Governance: Frameworks, processes, and best practices to guide the responsible and ethical development of AI solutions, ensuring alignment with legal requirements and customer interests.Levels of AI Maturity: AI maturity is often visualized as a spectrum or scale with several levels, typically ranging from1. Nascent: Limited understanding of AI, characterized by ad-hoc experimentation. 2. Developing: Formalization of an AI strategy begins, with initial projects underway.3. Operational: AI is integrated into some business processes, yielding measurable results.4. Transformative: AI is a core part of the company’s DNA, driving strategic decisions and creating significant competitive advantages.Let’s explore AI maturity for organizational success, recognizing there’s no one-size-fits-all approach. From my experience working with Nordic enterprises, I’ve identified three key dimensions within the AI maturity diagnostic process:Current State Assessment: Conduct a thorough analysis of the organization’s current AI capabilities, including infrastructure, data readiness, talent pools, and existing AI applications.Maturity Benchmarking: Compare the organization’s AI maturity with industry standards and identify areas for improvement.Gap Analysis and Recommendations: Provide detailed recommendations and a roadmap for achieving higher AI maturity.In our upcoming articles, we’ll explore the power of current state assessments, the importance of benchmarking in the AI race, and how to learn from leading AI-first companies to identify and overcome challenges quickly.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stockholm Cultural Night — A night to be remembered and cherished</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/27/stockholm-cultural-night-a-night-to-be-remembered-and-cherished.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stockholm Cultural Night — A night to be remembered and cherished" /><published>2022-04-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/27/stockholm-cultural-night-a-night-to-be-remembered-and-cherished</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/27/stockholm-cultural-night-a-night-to-be-remembered-and-cherished.html"><![CDATA[<h3>Stockholm Cultural Night — A night to be remembered and cherished</h3><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*nvxIBOS0URoIfLZh-SjyrQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>Stockholm Cultural Night at 23rd April 2022</figcaption></figure><p>The happening night for people who live in Stockholm. I am experiencing the cultural night at Stockholm for a first time and the weather played tricky at initial hours and was comfortable after times. I was accompanied by a young crowd and got an invitation from a friend of mine. We started with Swedish parliament visit but unfortunately we couldn’t get the guided tour since it’s super booked. The picture near the water in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helgeandsholmen">Helgeandsholmen</a> shows my excitement for the day.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/824/1*gPyVUHcB7Sqi8lwz3l9d0Q.png" /><figcaption>Lakshmikanth Rajamani’s picture near the Swedish parliament</figcaption></figure><p>It was windy and my friends started thinking about Belgium waffles and homemade ice creams. Unfortunately, my friends didn’t get the usual fruity Belgium waffles, so we went with <a href="https://stikkinikki.com/">Stikki Nikki</a> ice cream, it’s homemade and organic. It tasted great and I was fortunate enough to taste lemon-papaya combo, sunflower seeds with almond (vegan), and finally the regular one, milk and cookies. And we started walking towards <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Swedish_Opera">Kungliga Opera</a> for a ballet performance.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*8qiS9egWhuB6Vj10hYbzeA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Royal Swedish Opera</figcaption></figure><p>It was an awestruck experience with a live ballet performance. I know that it originated during the Italian Renaissance in the fifteenth century but I haven’t got a chance to check out a live performance. I should honestly thank the Stockholm Cultural Night team for making this possible.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fplayer.vimeo.com%2Fvideo%2F703511609%3Fh%3Ddd92a343b1%26app_id%3D122963&amp;dntp=1&amp;display_name=Vimeo&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fvimeo.com%2F703511609&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.vimeocdn.com%2Fvideo%2F1421033077-147e86f5c6511568d71bacd88f938e9c89901f14623acd7f27827166d99d716d-d_640&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=vimeo" width="720" height="1280" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/e82a065dc16bc414a8d61125ef1126e3/href">https://medium.com/media/e82a065dc16bc414a8d61125ef1126e3/href</a></iframe><p>There were three ultimate performances lined up on that day, that was magical and romantic. Then we rushed to visit the vasa museet from Gamla Stan. Actually my friends wanted to take part in a haunted city walk event but we couldn’t find the location though google maps was working fine and apple maps too. We took an old tram to commute from T-Centralen to Vasa Museet and it was a special ride though, the tram was house-full and we were barely standing on our toes during the entire ride.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fplayer.vimeo.com%2Fvideo%2F703517370%3Fh%3D220164b22a%26app_id%3D122963&amp;dntp=1&amp;display_name=Vimeo&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fvimeo.com%2F703517370&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.vimeocdn.com%2Fvideo%2F1421043036-53107d80bed771aa56dd2e32a4cb07de3dcbfb38ad7cd8c1063e281780152b54-d_960&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=vimeo" width="1080" height="1920" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/9f70c065d0562338049c54e836029ff5/href">https://medium.com/media/9f70c065d0562338049c54e836029ff5/href</a></iframe><p>Here comes the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasa_Museum">Vasa Museum</a>, located on the island of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djurg%C3%A5rden">Djurgården</a>. It displays the fully intact 17th-century ship that sank on her maiden voyage in 1628, and it’s the most visited museum in Scandinavia.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*8w6737z29Dz7yZNJO3C0Og.jpeg" /><figcaption>VASA Museum</figcaption></figure><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fplayer.vimeo.com%2Fvideo%2F703511815%3Fh%3D46899ffaba%26app_id%3D122963&amp;dntp=1&amp;display_name=Vimeo&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fvimeo.com%2F703511815&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.vimeocdn.com%2Fvideo%2F1421033485-71407f2edbf16bdf24d2168ad0ea2faab4e35c2f28472fb3f47f48d1e34de43a-d_960&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=vimeo" width="1080" height="1920" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/534263137fa9391463ba3153723d2bf4/href">https://medium.com/media/534263137fa9391463ba3153723d2bf4/href</a></iframe><p>It was crowded not because the entry is free during the Stockholm cultural night but for its rich experience and craftsmanship. And I forget to mention that all the shows/ events and museum visits on 23rd April 2022 are free!</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fplayer.vimeo.com%2Fvideo%2F703511695%3Fh%3D7e7eefadb2%26app_id%3D122963&amp;dntp=1&amp;display_name=Vimeo&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fvimeo.com%2F703511695&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.vimeocdn.com%2Fvideo%2F1421033381-8fd021362253a26dbf8a6cd183895da6da14c6f7244c0a6514e1c639a6e453ca-d_960&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=vimeo" width="1080" height="1920" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/c782f73b5287dc5ab5825be04c003d1e/href">https://medium.com/media/c782f73b5287dc5ab5825be04c003d1e/href</a></iframe><p>We found a man standing in a lengthy wood with a fire in his hand, at the Vasa Museet entrance welcoming the audience during the Stockholm Cultural Night.<br>Here are some of the pictures from the Vasa museum that I found interesting based on the art and design work.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*0d8PsmozE-X95h370ZmsQg.jpeg" /></figure><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*A-BF19S_W50EbUlijDCIhA.jpeg" /></figure><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*cRSOVXVEBTwgkrpzL2Zcmg.jpeg" /><figcaption>Pictures from the Vasa Museum</figcaption></figure><p>Later we had a chance to visit the Nordic Museum, located adjacent to the Vasa Museum. Nordic Museum is dedicated to cultural history of Sweden from the early modern period to the contemporary period. You can expect to experience the furniture, clothes and toys from the period mentioned above, also the sustainable earth and some interesting research on the ice and frozen creatures.</p><p>And interesting pictures from the Nordic Museum.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*foxHWGPQDqe6CgmmamXyMw.jpeg" /></figure><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*avLqSOfygdAcMn0JmGnKzA.jpeg" /></figure><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*ZOLqRR_VAToYs-acN7hyIA.jpeg" /></figure><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*vSXtiNf-teGon8SGgJ_sIQ.jpeg" /></figure><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*DVr_FCrlsY6aF2TuqPtM4g.jpeg" /></figure><p>Somehow we managed to join the DJ night and enjoyed it to the core. I could see almost everyone dancing and expressing their happiness after a pandemic occurrence.</p><p>I danced for a long time and enjoyed myself with my friends during the Stockholm Cultural Night and I would recommend anyone to take part in Stockholm Cultural Night in the upcoming years if you’re planning to Sweden during that event.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*-ZaYHzSjSy7E-W2hCbTHkA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Lakshmikanth and his friends at the Stockholm Cultural Night</figcaption></figure><p>It was perfectly organized and time-packed for a wide-audience group. One can explore dance, architecture, music, theatre, literature, and much more during this event. A big thanks to the city of Stockholm and the Culture Administration team for making it possible.</p><p>Thanks for taking the time to read about our experience with the Stockholm Cultural Night and the journey continues…</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fplayer.vimeo.com%2Fvideo%2F703511682%3Fh%3Db842fa755d%26app_id%3D122963&amp;dntp=1&amp;display_name=Vimeo&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fvimeo.com%2F703511682&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.vimeocdn.com%2Fvideo%2F1421033272-1fbc9342aa689df68d785367b45c1b559f6a5084f4b92352b56f8aed478dbbdb-d_960&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=vimeo" width="1080" height="1920" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/b3cd9321cddf6c825011a2bc17d9117b/href">https://medium.com/media/b3cd9321cddf6c825011a2bc17d9117b/href</a></iframe><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=69fb91d349db" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="swedish-museum" /><category term="cultural" /><category term="stockholm" /><category term="royal-swedish-opera" /><category term="stockholm-cultural-night" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stockholm Cultural Night — A night to be remembered and cherishedStockholm Cultural Night at 23rd April 2022The happening night for people who live in Stockholm. I am experiencing the cultural night at Stockholm for a first time and the weather played tricky at initial hours and was comfortable after times. I was accompanied by a young crowd and got an invitation from a friend of mine. We started with Swedish parliament visit but unfortunately we couldn’t get the guided tour since it’s super booked. The picture near the water in Helgeandsholmen shows my excitement for the day.Lakshmikanth Rajamani’s picture near the Swedish parliamentIt was windy and my friends started thinking about Belgium waffles and homemade ice creams. Unfortunately, my friends didn’t get the usual fruity Belgium waffles, so we went with Stikki Nikki ice cream, it’s homemade and organic. It tasted great and I was fortunate enough to taste lemon-papaya combo, sunflower seeds with almond (vegan), and finally the regular one, milk and cookies. And we started walking towards Kungliga Opera for a ballet performance.Royal Swedish OperaIt was an awestruck experience with a live ballet performance. I know that it originated during the Italian Renaissance in the fifteenth century but I haven’t got a chance to check out a live performance. I should honestly thank the Stockholm Cultural Night team for making this possible.https://medium.com/media/e82a065dc16bc414a8d61125ef1126e3/hrefThere were three ultimate performances lined up on that day, that was magical and romantic. Then we rushed to visit the vasa museet from Gamla Stan. Actually my friends wanted to take part in a haunted city walk event but we couldn’t find the location though google maps was working fine and apple maps too. We took an old tram to commute from T-Centralen to Vasa Museet and it was a special ride though, the tram was house-full and we were barely standing on our toes during the entire ride.https://medium.com/media/9f70c065d0562338049c54e836029ff5/hrefHere comes the Vasa Museum, located on the island of Djurgården. It displays the fully intact 17th-century ship that sank on her maiden voyage in 1628, and it’s the most visited museum in Scandinavia.VASA Museumhttps://medium.com/media/534263137fa9391463ba3153723d2bf4/hrefIt was crowded not because the entry is free during the Stockholm cultural night but for its rich experience and craftsmanship. And I forget to mention that all the shows/ events and museum visits on 23rd April 2022 are free!https://medium.com/media/c782f73b5287dc5ab5825be04c003d1e/hrefWe found a man standing in a lengthy wood with a fire in his hand, at the Vasa Museet entrance welcoming the audience during the Stockholm Cultural Night.Here are some of the pictures from the Vasa museum that I found interesting based on the art and design work.Pictures from the Vasa MuseumLater we had a chance to visit the Nordic Museum, located adjacent to the Vasa Museum. Nordic Museum is dedicated to cultural history of Sweden from the early modern period to the contemporary period. You can expect to experience the furniture, clothes and toys from the period mentioned above, also the sustainable earth and some interesting research on the ice and frozen creatures.And interesting pictures from the Nordic Museum.Somehow we managed to join the DJ night and enjoyed it to the core. I could see almost everyone dancing and expressing their happiness after a pandemic occurrence.I danced for a long time and enjoyed myself with my friends during the Stockholm Cultural Night and I would recommend anyone to take part in Stockholm Cultural Night in the upcoming years if you’re planning to Sweden during that event.Lakshmikanth and his friends at the Stockholm Cultural NightIt was perfectly organized and time-packed for a wide-audience group. One can explore dance, architecture, music, theatre, literature, and much more during this event. A big thanks to the city of Stockholm and the Culture Administration team for making it possible.Thanks for taking the time to read about our experience with the Stockholm Cultural Night and the journey continues…https://medium.com/media/b3cd9321cddf6c825011a2bc17d9117b/href]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Big Data helped US Women Cycle team move from underdogs to silver medalists at the 2012 London…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/22/how-big-data-helped-us-women-cycle-team-move-from-underdogs-to-silver-medalists-at-the-2012-london.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Big Data helped US Women Cycle team move from underdogs to silver medalists at the 2012 London…" /><published>2020-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/22/how-big-data-helped-us-women-cycle-team-move-from-underdogs-to-silver-medalists-at-the-2012-london</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/22/how-big-data-helped-us-women-cycle-team-move-from-underdogs-to-silver-medalists-at-the-2012-london.html"><![CDATA[<h3>How Big Data helped US Women Cycle team move from underdogs to silver medalists at the 2012 London Olympics</h3><p>Welcome to my #datastories series, where I talk about data and how it’s influencing businesses to take decisions at scale.</p><p>#datastories Series 1 - Story 1</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fgiphy.com%2Fembed%2F5hfinCirdgvzwlqaWU%2Ftwitter%2Fiframe&amp;display_name=Giphy&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fgiphy.com%2Fgifs%2FFC-URBAN-dance-welcome-fcurban-5hfinCirdgvzwlqaWU&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fmedia2.giphy.com%2Fmedia%2F5hfinCirdgvzwlqaWU%2Fgiphy.gif&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=giphy" width="435" height="435" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/ff81f92fef967f09c904e1b6fde1c041/href">https://medium.com/media/ff81f92fef967f09c904e1b6fde1c041/href</a></iframe><p>This story will help you understand how Big Data helped athletes to optimize their performance. People never thought sports and big data would become friends in the late ’90s. But later they understood things are moving in a different direction and developers started thinking why can’t we marry big data with any data-driven problems.</p><p>I would like to include a problem solved by a high school club that uses data science to predict which teams the NCAA will select for the Division I Men’s Basketball Tournament.</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/learning/bracketology-club-using-march-madness-to-learn-data-science/bracketology-club-using-march-madness-to-learn-data-science">Bracketology Club: Using March Madness to Learn Data Science - Bracketology Club: Using March Madness to Learn Data Science</a></p><p><strong>Back to the story:</strong> How the U.S. women’s cycling team used analytics to leap from underdog status to silver medalists at the 2012 London Olympics.</p><p>The team was struggling when it turned to Sky Christopherson for help. Christopherson, is an American <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entrepreneur">entrepreneur</a>, Olympic Athlete, World Record Holder, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_speaker">public speaker</a>. He is known for breaking a World Record<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sky_Christopherson#cite_note-rankings-6">[6]</a> in 2011 in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Velodrome">velodrome</a> sprint, notably using a ‘digital health’ model inspired by Dr. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_Topol">Eric Topol</a>. He started a community to help improve the US women’s cycle team’s possibilities of winning in the Olympics by identifying the secret sauce to success. He wanted to develop a program for athletes that consumed data to improve their performance instead of consuming drugs. He came up with OAthlete project, which helped find the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lance_Armstrong_doping_case">Lance Armstrong Drug Scandal</a></p><p><a href="https://bleacherreport.com/articles/1516420-lance-armstrong-is-the-dirtiest-cheater-in-sports-history">Lance Armstrong Is the Dirtiest Cheater in Sports History</a></p><p>The philosophy behind the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimized_Athlete">OAthlete</a> program is “<strong>data not drugs”</strong>. Christopherson came up with a sophisticated design to capture the athlete’s performance versus their diet, sleep patterns, environmental factors, training intensity, and whatever feature that can help find the pattern and help them perform better in Olympics. Big Data enables a high-performance sports team to quantify the many factors that influence performance. Which helped him to identify key elements and to plan their training accordingly with stopping of overtraining that often resulted in injury.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fgiphy.com%2Fembed%2FXEaxdA1mObxm40bnpM%2Ftwitter%2Fiframe&amp;display_name=Giphy&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fgiphy.com%2Fgifs%2FJoKoy-stop-seriously-jo-koy-XEaxdA1mObxm40bnpM&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fmedia2.giphy.com%2Fmedia%2FXEaxdA1mObxm40bnpM%2Fgiphy.gif&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=giphy" width="435" height="435" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/a265242e44dcaf9ec2f1540bfc573426/href">https://medium.com/media/a265242e44dcaf9ec2f1540bfc573426/href</a></iframe><p>Data captured from athletes were structured and unstructured. It mainly had information such as blood sugar level, skin parameters, pulse, ambient information, sleeping patterns, and diet. Christopherson partnered with <a href="https://www.datameer.com/">Datameer</a>, San Francisco based data analytics provider. Where the data is pushed to the cloud in a Hadoop Distributed File System and the company was analyzing their data and coming up with a dashboard for helping the athletes.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2Fn5eQsCM-QB0%3Ffeature%3Doembed&amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3Dn5eQsCM-QB0&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2Fn5eQsCM-QB0%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/8df5c6824573163a6511c0da989aaa38/href">https://medium.com/media/8df5c6824573163a6511c0da989aaa38/href</a></iframe><p>Domain knowledge plays an important role in any industry for solving real-world problems. Christopherson partnered with Datameer to help optimize the athlete’s performance. Datameer’s CEO, Stefan Groschupf, himself a former competitive swimmer at a national level in Germany, immediately saw the potential of the project. Christopherson said “They came back with some really exciting results — some connections that we hadn’t seen before. How diet, training, and environment all influence each other — everything is interconnected and you can really see that in the data.”</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*Cz-KrcjtVQa79s5j.jpg" /><figcaption>Data analysis of Athlete’s performance</figcaption></figure><p>Here the idea is to find patterns across different datasets and combining the knowledge to really improve the performance of the athletes to ensure their possibilities of winning in the Olympics.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2Fb1c2EvzjOgk&amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3Db1c2EvzjOgk&amp;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2Fb1c2EvzjOgk%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/4ae235f5554f6086da459afabe3128e0/href">https://medium.com/media/4ae235f5554f6086da459afabe3128e0/href</a></iframe><h3>Credits</h3><ol><li><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2015/06/08/big-data-not-doping-how-the-u-s-olympic-womens-cycling-team-competes-on-analytics/#6c7acc553be5">https://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2015/06/08/big-data-not-doping-how-the-u-s-olympic-womens-cycling-team-competes-on-analytics/#6c7acc553be5</a></li><li><a href="https://themagnumgroup.net/Blog/big-data-olympic-cyclists/">https://themagnumgroup.net/Blog/big-data-olympic-cyclists/</a></li><li><a href="https://www.si.com/edge/2015/05/14/personal-gold-documentary-us-womens-cycling-team">https://www.si.com/edge/2015/05/14/personal-gold-documentary-us-womens-cycling-team</a></li><li><a href="https://hginsights.com/blog/big-data-performance-enhancing-method-olympics/">https://hginsights.com/blog/big-data-performance-enhancing-method-olympics/</a></li><li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sky_Christopherson">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sky_Christopherson</a></li><li><a href="https://www.datameer.com/news/u-s-womens-cycling-team-wins-silver-medal-in-london-olympics-using-big-data-analytics/">https://www.datameer.com/news/u-s-womens-cycling-team-wins-silver-medal-in-london-olympics-using-big-data-analytics/</a></li><li><a href="https://giphy.com/">https://giphy.com/</a> (GIF gallery)</li></ol><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=52594d409163" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-science" /><category term="storytelling" /><category term="big-data" /><category term="sports" /><category term="data-analysis" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Big Data helped US Women Cycle team move from underdogs to silver medalists at the 2012 London OlympicsWelcome to my #datastories series, where I talk about data and how it’s influencing businesses to take decisions at scale.#datastories Series 1 - Story 1https://medium.com/media/ff81f92fef967f09c904e1b6fde1c041/hrefThis story will help you understand how Big Data helped athletes to optimize their performance. People never thought sports and big data would become friends in the late ’90s. But later they understood things are moving in a different direction and developers started thinking why can’t we marry big data with any data-driven problems.I would like to include a problem solved by a high school club that uses data science to predict which teams the NCAA will select for the Division I Men’s Basketball Tournament.Bracketology Club: Using March Madness to Learn Data Science - Bracketology Club: Using March Madness to Learn Data ScienceBack to the story: How the U.S. women’s cycling team used analytics to leap from underdog status to silver medalists at the 2012 London Olympics.The team was struggling when it turned to Sky Christopherson for help. Christopherson, is an American entrepreneur, Olympic Athlete, World Record Holder, and public speaker. He is known for breaking a World Record[6] in 2011 in the velodrome sprint, notably using a ‘digital health’ model inspired by Dr. Eric Topol. He started a community to help improve the US women’s cycle team’s possibilities of winning in the Olympics by identifying the secret sauce to success. He wanted to develop a program for athletes that consumed data to improve their performance instead of consuming drugs. He came up with OAthlete project, which helped find the Lance Armstrong Drug ScandalLance Armstrong Is the Dirtiest Cheater in Sports HistoryThe philosophy behind the OAthlete program is “data not drugs”. Christopherson came up with a sophisticated design to capture the athlete’s performance versus their diet, sleep patterns, environmental factors, training intensity, and whatever feature that can help find the pattern and help them perform better in Olympics. Big Data enables a high-performance sports team to quantify the many factors that influence performance. Which helped him to identify key elements and to plan their training accordingly with stopping of overtraining that often resulted in injury.https://medium.com/media/a265242e44dcaf9ec2f1540bfc573426/hrefData captured from athletes were structured and unstructured. It mainly had information such as blood sugar level, skin parameters, pulse, ambient information, sleeping patterns, and diet. Christopherson partnered with Datameer, San Francisco based data analytics provider. Where the data is pushed to the cloud in a Hadoop Distributed File System and the company was analyzing their data and coming up with a dashboard for helping the athletes.https://medium.com/media/8df5c6824573163a6511c0da989aaa38/hrefDomain knowledge plays an important role in any industry for solving real-world problems. Christopherson partnered with Datameer to help optimize the athlete’s performance. Datameer’s CEO, Stefan Groschupf, himself a former competitive swimmer at a national level in Germany, immediately saw the potential of the project. Christopherson said “They came back with some really exciting results — some connections that we hadn’t seen before. How diet, training, and environment all influence each other — everything is interconnected and you can really see that in the data.”Data analysis of Athlete’s performanceHere the idea is to find patterns across different datasets and combining the knowledge to really improve the performance of the athletes to ensure their possibilities of winning in the Olympics.https://medium.com/media/4ae235f5554f6086da459afabe3128e0/hrefCreditshttps://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2015/06/08/big-data-not-doping-how-the-u-s-olympic-womens-cycling-team-competes-on-analytics/#6c7acc553be5https://themagnumgroup.net/Blog/big-data-olympic-cyclists/https://www.si.com/edge/2015/05/14/personal-gold-documentary-us-womens-cycling-teamhttps://hginsights.com/blog/big-data-performance-enhancing-method-olympics/https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sky_Christophersonhttps://www.datameer.com/news/u-s-womens-cycling-team-wins-silver-medal-in-london-olympics-using-big-data-analytics/https://giphy.com/ (GIF gallery)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dealing with bias in AI algorithms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/dealing-with-bias-in-ai-algorithms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dealing with bias in AI algorithms" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/dealing-with-bias-in-ai-algorithms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/dealing-with-bias-in-ai-algorithms.html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog is inspired by a ted video presented by <a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a></p><h4>Introduction about <a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a>,</h4><p>She’s an MIT grad student working with facial analysis software when she noticed a problem: the software didn’t detect her face — because the people who coded the algorithm hadn’t taught it to identify a broad range of skin tones and facial structures. Now she’s on a mission to fight bias in machine learning, a phenomenon she calls the “coded gaze.” It’s an eye-opening talk about the need for accountability in coding … as algorithms take over more and more aspects of our lives. Her research explores the intersection of social impact technology and inclusion.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*ksI7dNZsINxXYgY3BLGZfA.jpeg" /><figcaption><a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a></figcaption></figure><h4>What’s Algorithmic bias?</h4><p>Algorithmic bias describes <strong>systematic</strong> and <strong>repeatable errors</strong> in a computer system that create <strong>unfair outcomes</strong>, such as privileging one arbitrary group of users over others. Bias can emerge due to many factors, including but not limited to the<strong> design of the algorithm</strong> or the unintended or unanticipated use or decisions relating to the way data is <strong>coded, collected, selected</strong>, or used to <strong>train the algorithm</strong>. Algorithmic bias is found across platforms, including but not limited to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Search_engine_bias">search engine results</a> and social media platforms, and can have impacts ranging from inadvertent privacy violations to reinforcing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bias">social biases</a> of <strong>race, gender, sexuality, and ethnicit</strong>y. The study of algorithmic bias is most concerned with algorithms that reflect “systematic and unfair” discrimination.</p><p><strong>Why Algorithmic Bias matter?<br></strong>It started when <a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a> wanted to test her face on a camera-enabled to detect/identify the face of humans for computational processing; wherein the camera detected the people with light skin and demanded dark skin people to wear a white mask to detect their faces.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*41ZoldQNgLyrhJGHaJgjRQ.png" /><figcaption><a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a> involved in a project during her undergraduate to enable a robot to play peek-a-boo</figcaption></figure><p>It happened to her once she was involved in a project during her undergraduate program to train a robot to play peek-a-boo (where robot played actively with her roommates of lighter skin and failed to detect her face often)and it again happened to her at an entrepreneurship competition.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*g2ZpqBPUlbA9NEinMjWMEA.png" /><figcaption><a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a> at an entrepreneur competition (Hong Kong)</figcaption></figure><h4>What’s the Aspire Mirror?</h4><p><strong>Aspire mirror</strong> (a project by <a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a>) is a device that enables you to look at yourself and see a reflection on your face based on what inspires you or what you hope to empathize with. Where she used a generic facial recognition software and it couldn’t detect her in a row; the solution for this problem would be creating a full-spectrum training set that will reflect a richer portrait of humanity.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/888/1*Q77ljcftlybstqc-j7Bh-g.jpeg" /><figcaption>Aspire Mirror Project Picture as available in the internet</figcaption></figure><h4>Why people should read this book “Weapons of Math destruction” written by Cathy O’Neil?</h4><p>Cause the author talks about the importance of WMD (Widespread, Mysterious, and Destructive Algorithms). She analyses how the use of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_data">big data</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithm">algorithms</a> in a variety of fields, including insurance, advertising, education, and policing, can lead to decisions that harm the poor, reinforce <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Racism">racism</a>, and amplify inequality.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/220/1*LrRNzzHXOnrIpOBCnHghFA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Weapons of Math Destruction by Cathy O’Neil</figcaption></figure><p>Most troubling, they reinforce discrimination: If a poor student can’t get a loan because a lending model deems him too risky (by his zip code), he’s then cut off from the kind of education that could pull him out of poverty, and a vicious spiral ensues. Models are propping up the lucky and punishing the downtrodden, creating a “toxic cocktail for democracy.”</p><p><a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a> wants people to be an inclusive coder. She focuses on three aspects of developing things concerning inclusion and they’re</p><ol><li>Who code matters</li><li>How we code matters</li><li>Why we code matters</li></ol><p>By following the above aspect we have an option to unlock the inequality if we consider a social change a priority. Also, we should try identifying the bias and curate inclusiveness with conscientious development to fight against the inequality in the algorithm inferences. <a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a> wants people to join Algorithmic Justice League (<a href="https://ajlunited.org">https://ajlunited.org</a>) to fight against the inequality in the algorithms available in the market by conveying that <strong>technology should serve all of us and not just the privileged few.</strong></p><h4>What is Gender Shades?</h4><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/483/1*v-tV6tBJAx-VmIoeQPceMA.png" /><figcaption><a href="https://medium.com/u/6343c11d8f21">Joy Buolamwini</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/u/2e2b7ed6c4f5">Timnit Gebru</a>; researchers from Gender Shades project</figcaption></figure><p>Gender Shades in detail: <strong>Intersectional Accuracy Disparities in Commercial Gender Classification. </strong>Gender Shades is an approach to evaluate bias present in automated facial analysis algorithms and datasets concerning phenotypic subgroups.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*iJMCbe4j3ga0G1PY9KwRrw.png" /></figure><p>From the abstract: The substantial disparities in the accuracy of classifying darker females, lighter females, darker males, and lighter males in gender classification systems require urgent attention if commercial companies are to build genuinely fair, transparent and accountable facial analysis algorithms</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/885/1*Q31H5i7CT52ZPCx6Oarqcw.png" /><figcaption>Research outcome from Gender Shades</figcaption></figure><p>Gender Shades research worked on the models that are made available for commercial needs from Microsoft, Face++, and IBM. And the final accuracy metrics were <strong>Microsoft (93.7%) &gt; Face++ (90.0%) &gt; IBM had (87.9%) </strong>From the results, all companies performed better on males and even better results with lighter skin than darker ones. In particular, all the companies performed badly at darker females. One of the finest practices for gender inequality in real-time was, <strong>Woman, are less likely to be shown ads for high paying jobs on Google</strong> (since most of the executives are male-dominant — an algorithm learns in such a way)</p><h4>Final thoughts,</h4><blockquote>We’re entered into a world of automation with over confident and under prepared. We should develop/ train machine make contextual decisions with inclusiveness and practicality in nature. Machine neutrality is expected across the globe and hence technology should serve all of us and not just the privileged few.</blockquote><h4>Credits</h4><ol><li>Algorithmic Bias <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithmic_bias">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithmic_bias</a></li><li>Joy Buolamwini Image <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ac/Joy_Buolamwini_-_Wikimania_2018_01.jpg">https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ac/Joy_Buolamwini_-_Wikimania_2018_01.jpg</a></li><li>Ted Talk <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/joy_buolamwini_how_i_m_fighting_bias_in_algorithms?language=en">https://www.ted.com/talks/joy_buolamwini_how_i_m_fighting_bias_in_algorithms?language=en</a></li><li>Algorithmic Justice League <a href="https://ajlunited.org">https://ajlunited.org</a></li><li>Gender Shades <a href="http://proceedings.mlr.press/v81/buolamwini18a/buolamwini18a.pdf">http://proceedings.mlr.press/v81/buolamwini18a/buolamwini18a.pdf</a></li><li>When the Robot Doesn’t See Dark Skin <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/21/opinion/facial-analysis-technology-bias.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/21/opinion/facial-analysis-technology-bias.html</a></li><li>AI, Ain’t I a Woman <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QxuyfWoVV98">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QxuyfWoVV98</a></li><li>Not Flawless <a href="https://www.notflawless.ai">https://www.notflawless.ai</a></li><li>Aspire Mirror <a href="http://www.aspiremirror.com">http://www.aspiremirror.com</a></li><li>Race &amp; Gender in Tech <a href="http://www.sigcas.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/LeeCSG2019.pdf">http://www.sigcas.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/LeeCSG2019.pdf</a></li></ol><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=e019e2d202ea" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="inclusive-ai" /><category term="ai-decision-making" /><category term="algorithmic-bias" /><category term="gender-bias-in-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog is inspired by a ted video presented by Joy BuolamwiniIntroduction about Joy Buolamwini,She’s an MIT grad student working with facial analysis software when she noticed a problem: the software didn’t detect her face — because the people who coded the algorithm hadn’t taught it to identify a broad range of skin tones and facial structures. Now she’s on a mission to fight bias in machine learning, a phenomenon she calls the “coded gaze.” It’s an eye-opening talk about the need for accountability in coding … as algorithms take over more and more aspects of our lives. Her research explores the intersection of social impact technology and inclusion.Joy BuolamwiniWhat’s Algorithmic bias?Algorithmic bias describes systematic and repeatable errors in a computer system that create unfair outcomes, such as privileging one arbitrary group of users over others. Bias can emerge due to many factors, including but not limited to the design of the algorithm or the unintended or unanticipated use or decisions relating to the way data is coded, collected, selected, or used to train the algorithm. Algorithmic bias is found across platforms, including but not limited to search engine results and social media platforms, and can have impacts ranging from inadvertent privacy violations to reinforcing social biases of race, gender, sexuality, and ethnicity. The study of algorithmic bias is most concerned with algorithms that reflect “systematic and unfair” discrimination.Why Algorithmic Bias matter?It started when Joy Buolamwini wanted to test her face on a camera-enabled to detect/identify the face of humans for computational processing; wherein the camera detected the people with light skin and demanded dark skin people to wear a white mask to detect their faces.Joy Buolamwini involved in a project during her undergraduate to enable a robot to play peek-a-booIt happened to her once she was involved in a project during her undergraduate program to train a robot to play peek-a-boo (where robot played actively with her roommates of lighter skin and failed to detect her face often)and it again happened to her at an entrepreneurship competition.Joy Buolamwini at an entrepreneur competition (Hong Kong)What’s the Aspire Mirror?Aspire mirror (a project by Joy Buolamwini) is a device that enables you to look at yourself and see a reflection on your face based on what inspires you or what you hope to empathize with. Where she used a generic facial recognition software and it couldn’t detect her in a row; the solution for this problem would be creating a full-spectrum training set that will reflect a richer portrait of humanity.Aspire Mirror Project Picture as available in the internetWhy people should read this book “Weapons of Math destruction” written by Cathy O’Neil?Cause the author talks about the importance of WMD (Widespread, Mysterious, and Destructive Algorithms). She analyses how the use of big data and algorithms in a variety of fields, including insurance, advertising, education, and policing, can lead to decisions that harm the poor, reinforce racism, and amplify inequality.Weapons of Math Destruction by Cathy O’NeilMost troubling, they reinforce discrimination: If a poor student can’t get a loan because a lending model deems him too risky (by his zip code), he’s then cut off from the kind of education that could pull him out of poverty, and a vicious spiral ensues. Models are propping up the lucky and punishing the downtrodden, creating a “toxic cocktail for democracy.”Joy Buolamwini wants people to be an inclusive coder. She focuses on three aspects of developing things concerning inclusion and they’reWho code mattersHow we code mattersWhy we code mattersBy following the above aspect we have an option to unlock the inequality if we consider a social change a priority. Also, we should try identifying the bias and curate inclusiveness with conscientious development to fight against the inequality in the algorithm inferences. Joy Buolamwini wants people to join Algorithmic Justice League (https://ajlunited.org) to fight against the inequality in the algorithms available in the market by conveying that technology should serve all of us and not just the privileged few.What is Gender Shades?Joy Buolamwini and Timnit Gebru; researchers from Gender Shades projectGender Shades in detail: Intersectional Accuracy Disparities in Commercial Gender Classification. Gender Shades is an approach to evaluate bias present in automated facial analysis algorithms and datasets concerning phenotypic subgroups.From the abstract: The substantial disparities in the accuracy of classifying darker females, lighter females, darker males, and lighter males in gender classification systems require urgent attention if commercial companies are to build genuinely fair, transparent and accountable facial analysis algorithmsResearch outcome from Gender ShadesGender Shades research worked on the models that are made available for commercial needs from Microsoft, Face++, and IBM. And the final accuracy metrics were Microsoft (93.7%) &gt; Face++ (90.0%) &gt; IBM had (87.9%) From the results, all companies performed better on males and even better results with lighter skin than darker ones. In particular, all the companies performed badly at darker females. One of the finest practices for gender inequality in real-time was, Woman, are less likely to be shown ads for high paying jobs on Google (since most of the executives are male-dominant — an algorithm learns in such a way)Final thoughts,We’re entered into a world of automation with over confident and under prepared. We should develop/ train machine make contextual decisions with inclusiveness and practicality in nature. Machine neutrality is expected across the globe and hence technology should serve all of us and not just the privileged few.CreditsAlgorithmic Bias https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithmic_biasJoy Buolamwini Image https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ac/Joy_Buolamwini_-_Wikimania_2018_01.jpgTed Talk https://www.ted.com/talks/joy_buolamwini_how_i_m_fighting_bias_in_algorithms?language=enAlgorithmic Justice League https://ajlunited.orgGender Shades http://proceedings.mlr.press/v81/buolamwini18a/buolamwini18a.pdfWhen the Robot Doesn’t See Dark Skin https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/21/opinion/facial-analysis-technology-bias.htmlAI, Ain’t I a Woman https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QxuyfWoVV98Not Flawless https://www.notflawless.aiAspire Mirror http://www.aspiremirror.comRace &amp; Gender in Tech http://www.sigcas.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/LeeCSG2019.pdf]]></summary></entry></feed>