<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-23T01:14:23+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Insights from the Experienced</title><subtitle>I am a software engineering professional, writes about engineering, food and economics.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Building Cloudlagom: Balancing Innovation and Cloud Costs with AI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/09/building-cloudlagom-balancing-innovation-and-cloud-costs-with-ai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Cloudlagom: Balancing Innovation and Cloud Costs with AI" /><published>2025-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/01/09/building-cloudlagom-balancing-innovation-and-cloud-costs-with-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/09/building-cloudlagom-balancing-innovation-and-cloud-costs-with-ai.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*evhtlXTN09niSp1gvZDEow.jpeg" /><figcaption>Christmas at Skansen, Sweden</figcaption></figure><p>I’m a software enthusiast and a digital nomad. I enjoy experimenting with software and exploring digital products across various categories, similar to window shopping in a mall. My passion for computers began early. I spent most of my time playing games and creating fun assets using paint and PowerPoint.</p><p>In primary school, I was introduced to coding. I remember programming in computer graphics and building simple HTML interfaces. My computer teachers introduced me to different tools and strengthened my foundation, enabling me to understand paradigms and new concepts even now. In high school, I was forced to choose computer science as a major despite my interest in biology. Later, I pursued a computer science engineering course from Anna University. I never regretted taking an interesting course. I learned a lot about cloud and distributed computing, data mining and science, AI, and mobile engineering.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*bTwGgUvpaHjoy_LkSP9UIQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>Christmas Market, Skansen</figcaption></figure><p>During my university years, I built my first startup and started consulting projects. I also developed projects for my seniors to support their final-year projects and created apps for small and medium-sized businesses. When I couldn’t sell my creations, I decided to work for a consulting company. There, I learned pre-sales, which involves selling technical solutions or products to customers. It wasn’t actual selling but rather enabling sales by understanding technical requirements. For instance, I built proof of concepts and inspired customers that my solution could help them improve their business operations. Believe me, it’s an interesting area to work in because you learn to engineer software solutions (design, develop, and deploy) for different business cases and interact with customers, sharing your experiences and solving their pain points. It’s like having two mangoes with a stone. From the beginning, I focused on improving my research and engineering skills in the data and AI areas, without fancy titles. I knew this would be the future in early 2015.</p><p>Later, I was allowed to lead AI engagement for the company, developing an Enterprise AI product for 400,000 consultants and their customers with a small team of five, mostly constrained by limited resources. Most of the team consisted of fresh graduates. I was tasked with training and building the product, which was undoubtedly a challenging endeavour. I had to help them grasp the fundamentals of technology, which was difficult at the time because there were no adequate learning resources available, such as videos and course content for Data Science and AI. During that period, I created some content to support their learning journey, which was both enjoyable and demanding. Later, I demonstrated the value of the product that my team and I had built. The company sponsored my team’s expansion, hired senior professionals, and established a dedicated team focused on AI research and product development. I had the privilege of meeting many great people during that time, some of whom became close friends. I am grateful for those connections.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*bKAzFkJarm8KTroIB4iKIQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>Some more pictures from Skansen</figcaption></figure><p>Before embarking on this AI suite project, I had experience working on optimisation solutions for power plants aimed at improving energy efficiency and reducing the release of harmful gases into the environment while adhering to compliance standards. I also developed recommendation engines for commerce customers and data mining and statistical models for banking customers. We launched low-code AI tools for business users, which helped accelerate the development of AI systems. However, shortly after that, the senior sponsors at the organization retired, leading to a significant reorganization within the company. This change forced me to relocate to work with the cloud business division of the company. I chose Google Cloud as my preferred platform because I am passionate about data, AI, and innovation, which are the core principles of Google Cloud. I moved from India to Scandinavia to assist customers in designing and developing solutions on Google Cloud. I gained expertise in a wide range of data engineering, data science, and AI tools, including Databricks, BigQuery, Driverless AI, Vertex AI, and Sagemaker.</p><p>I had always been entrepreneurial, so I decided to leave the consulting company that offered me diverse opportunities in India and Scandinavia to join a small consulting startup as a Principal Consultant with the goal of becoming a partner. When I joined, the company was small and focused solely on cloud advisory and project management, with only a handful of employees. However, within a few months, we were able to grow to 15 people thanks to the investment from the management company, a sister company that helped us secure more clients because many of their clients became ours. Cloud technology is transformative, and so are our clients. After a year, I joined the company, which was acquired by another consulting company in Stockholm with over 4,000 consultants. Our unique selling proposition was that we were mostly hybrid consultants, meaning we could work on both management and technology problems, which aligned with the new company that acquired us. I continued to focus on cloud and AI consulting, leading AI initiatives in the new company and also helping to expand the Google Cloud Partnerships for them. While I was comfortable with the team, resources, and opportunities to grow my aspirations, the challenges were not particularly demanding, so I decided to leave the company in Sweden and move to London, UK.</p><p>And another reason was my marriage. Last summer, I married a UK citizen and had to decide between staying in Sweden or moving to London. While my wife preferred living in London, I wanted to support her decision, so I left Sweden and moved with her. After moving to London, I didn’t find any exciting opportunities that aligned with my interests or passions. Throughout my career, the only consistent challenge I faced in the software industry was the grey area surrounding software costs. This issue was also prevalent among most of my developer and architect friends, especially since we were in the midst of the cloud era. In this era, most software development and deployment activities took place in the cloud, and the teams responsible for these activities were concerned about the costs they were accountable for. This realisation sparked an idea in me: what if we could solve the grey area of eliminating the worry about costs for developers and architects using AI agents? That’s how Cloudlagom was born.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*MKp1pSEqIkF1RlxTIQSNsw.jpeg" /><figcaption>While moving from Sweden to London, a picture from Norwegian flight</figcaption></figure><p>Lagom, a Swedish concept meaning “the right amount,” has inspired Cloudlagom, your AI companion for building cloud resources in a balanced manner that aligns with your business needs. Developers and architects can now rest assured that Cloudlagom will handle cloud costs, eliminating the need for manual intervention. My goal is to make Cloudlagom publicly accessible, ensuring its usability and impact on users. Our software will exclusively focus on optimising cloud costs, outperforming any other solution in the market. Ultimately, Cloudlagom aims to bridge the gap between business contexts and cloud product knowledge, providing a comprehensive understanding of cloud opportunities. Currently, cloud vendors’ AI excels in managing their cloud products but cannot comprehend business contexts and effectively resize opportunities accordingly. This is where Cloudlagom’s potential lies.</p><p>As a founding member of the company, I will be dedicated to overseeing company operations, product engineering, sales, and marketing. I plan to create valuable content, including blogs, videos, and other resources that benefit both users and the company. I aspire to gain insights into cloud users’ experiences and develop strategies to enhance their relationship with cloud costs. Additionally, I aim to provide AI-powered insights and foster Cloudlagom’s growth as a trusted partner for our customers.</p><p>If you’re here, thank you for taking the time to read my essay. I truly appreciate your support, and I’m excited to continue writing about Cloudlagom in the future.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=66dad0be9cea" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cloud-computing" /><category term="cloudlagom" /><category term="software-company" /><category term="cloud-cost-optimization" /><category term="software-startup" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Christmas at Skansen, SwedenI’m a software enthusiast and a digital nomad. I enjoy experimenting with software and exploring digital products across various categories, similar to window shopping in a mall. My passion for computers began early. I spent most of my time playing games and creating fun assets using paint and PowerPoint.In primary school, I was introduced to coding. I remember programming in computer graphics and building simple HTML interfaces. My computer teachers introduced me to different tools and strengthened my foundation, enabling me to understand paradigms and new concepts even now. In high school, I was forced to choose computer science as a major despite my interest in biology. Later, I pursued a computer science engineering course from Anna University. I never regretted taking an interesting course. I learned a lot about cloud and distributed computing, data mining and science, AI, and mobile engineering.Christmas Market, SkansenDuring my university years, I built my first startup and started consulting projects. I also developed projects for my seniors to support their final-year projects and created apps for small and medium-sized businesses. When I couldn’t sell my creations, I decided to work for a consulting company. There, I learned pre-sales, which involves selling technical solutions or products to customers. It wasn’t actual selling but rather enabling sales by understanding technical requirements. For instance, I built proof of concepts and inspired customers that my solution could help them improve their business operations. Believe me, it’s an interesting area to work in because you learn to engineer software solutions (design, develop, and deploy) for different business cases and interact with customers, sharing your experiences and solving their pain points. It’s like having two mangoes with a stone. From the beginning, I focused on improving my research and engineering skills in the data and AI areas, without fancy titles. I knew this would be the future in early 2015.Later, I was allowed to lead AI engagement for the company, developing an Enterprise AI product for 400,000 consultants and their customers with a small team of five, mostly constrained by limited resources. Most of the team consisted of fresh graduates. I was tasked with training and building the product, which was undoubtedly a challenging endeavour. I had to help them grasp the fundamentals of technology, which was difficult at the time because there were no adequate learning resources available, such as videos and course content for Data Science and AI. During that period, I created some content to support their learning journey, which was both enjoyable and demanding. Later, I demonstrated the value of the product that my team and I had built. The company sponsored my team’s expansion, hired senior professionals, and established a dedicated team focused on AI research and product development. I had the privilege of meeting many great people during that time, some of whom became close friends. I am grateful for those connections.Some more pictures from SkansenBefore embarking on this AI suite project, I had experience working on optimisation solutions for power plants aimed at improving energy efficiency and reducing the release of harmful gases into the environment while adhering to compliance standards. I also developed recommendation engines for commerce customers and data mining and statistical models for banking customers. We launched low-code AI tools for business users, which helped accelerate the development of AI systems. However, shortly after that, the senior sponsors at the organization retired, leading to a significant reorganization within the company. This change forced me to relocate to work with the cloud business division of the company. I chose Google Cloud as my preferred platform because I am passionate about data, AI, and innovation, which are the core principles of Google Cloud. I moved from India to Scandinavia to assist customers in designing and developing solutions on Google Cloud. I gained expertise in a wide range of data engineering, data science, and AI tools, including Databricks, BigQuery, Driverless AI, Vertex AI, and Sagemaker.I had always been entrepreneurial, so I decided to leave the consulting company that offered me diverse opportunities in India and Scandinavia to join a small consulting startup as a Principal Consultant with the goal of becoming a partner. When I joined, the company was small and focused solely on cloud advisory and project management, with only a handful of employees. However, within a few months, we were able to grow to 15 people thanks to the investment from the management company, a sister company that helped us secure more clients because many of their clients became ours. Cloud technology is transformative, and so are our clients. After a year, I joined the company, which was acquired by another consulting company in Stockholm with over 4,000 consultants. Our unique selling proposition was that we were mostly hybrid consultants, meaning we could work on both management and technology problems, which aligned with the new company that acquired us. I continued to focus on cloud and AI consulting, leading AI initiatives in the new company and also helping to expand the Google Cloud Partnerships for them. While I was comfortable with the team, resources, and opportunities to grow my aspirations, the challenges were not particularly demanding, so I decided to leave the company in Sweden and move to London, UK.And another reason was my marriage. Last summer, I married a UK citizen and had to decide between staying in Sweden or moving to London. While my wife preferred living in London, I wanted to support her decision, so I left Sweden and moved with her. After moving to London, I didn’t find any exciting opportunities that aligned with my interests or passions. Throughout my career, the only consistent challenge I faced in the software industry was the grey area surrounding software costs. This issue was also prevalent among most of my developer and architect friends, especially since we were in the midst of the cloud era. In this era, most software development and deployment activities took place in the cloud, and the teams responsible for these activities were concerned about the costs they were accountable for. This realisation sparked an idea in me: what if we could solve the grey area of eliminating the worry about costs for developers and architects using AI agents? That’s how Cloudlagom was born.While moving from Sweden to London, a picture from Norwegian flightLagom, a Swedish concept meaning “the right amount,” has inspired Cloudlagom, your AI companion for building cloud resources in a balanced manner that aligns with your business needs. Developers and architects can now rest assured that Cloudlagom will handle cloud costs, eliminating the need for manual intervention. My goal is to make Cloudlagom publicly accessible, ensuring its usability and impact on users. Our software will exclusively focus on optimising cloud costs, outperforming any other solution in the market. Ultimately, Cloudlagom aims to bridge the gap between business contexts and cloud product knowledge, providing a comprehensive understanding of cloud opportunities. Currently, cloud vendors’ AI excels in managing their cloud products but cannot comprehend business contexts and effectively resize opportunities accordingly. This is where Cloudlagom’s potential lies.As a founding member of the company, I will be dedicated to overseeing company operations, product engineering, sales, and marketing. I plan to create valuable content, including blogs, videos, and other resources that benefit both users and the company. I aspire to gain insights into cloud users’ experiences and develop strategies to enhance their relationship with cloud costs. Additionally, I aim to provide AI-powered insights and foster Cloudlagom’s growth as a trusted partner for our customers.If you’re here, thank you for taking the time to read my essay. I truly appreciate your support, and I’m excited to continue writing about Cloudlagom in the future.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DevFest London 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/19/devfest-london-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DevFest London 2024" /><published>2024-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/19/devfest-london-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/19/devfest-london-2024.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have attended DevFest events around the globe — from India to Sweden, Norway, and the UK. DevFest London was a standout experience this year, buzzing with the energy of 28 speakers, 4 tracks, and over 260 attendees.</p><figure><img alt="A close-up of the DevFest London 2024 attendee badge" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*tb85qMzy3eBk4qfqo0aE1Q.jpeg" /><figcaption>A close-up of the DevFest London 2024 attendee badge</figcaption></figure><p>Having previously presented on cloud, data, AI platforms, and responsible AI in Stockholm and India, I was naturally drawn to the AI track. The sessions were a fascinating exploration of cutting-edge topics, ranging from:</p><ul><li><strong>Generative AI model performance:</strong> A deep dive into the capabilities and limitations of today’s most advanced AI models.</li><li><strong>Prompt injection attacks:</strong> A critical look at the security vulnerabilities of LLMs and how to mitigate them.</li><li><strong>Avoiding common LLM pitfalls:</strong> Practical advice on navigating the challenges of working with large language models.</li><li><strong>The rise of LVMs:</strong> Insights into why Large Vision Models are poised to revolutionize how we interact with visual data.</li><li><strong>Harnessing the power of Gemini:</strong> Expert tips on leveraging Google’s latest AI model while staying within ethical boundaries.</li><li><strong>AutoML with Vertex AI:</strong> Empowering business users to build and deploy machine learning models without coding expertise.</li><li><strong>Google’s Secure AI Framework (SAIF):</strong> A comprehensive overview of Google’s approach to building secure and trustworthy AI systems.</li></ul><figure><img alt="Banner displaying the logos of companies sponsoring DevFest London 2024" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*haDilQr_tmCOfu2HaD0udw.jpeg" /><figcaption>Banner displaying the logos of companies sponsoring DevFest London 2024</figcaption></figure><p><strong>My DevFest secret weapon: </strong><a href="https://www.granola.ai/"><strong>granola.ai</strong></a></p><p>In the whirlwind of back-to-back sessions, I discovered a game-changer: <a href="https://www.granola.ai/"><strong>granola.ai</strong></a>. This incredible tool transcribed the sessions in real-time, allowing me to fully engage with the presentations without worrying about taking notes. If you’re a meeting maestro juggling a packed schedule, <a href="https://www.granola.ai/">granola.ai</a> is your new best friend.</p><p><strong>Taking LLMs offline with Ollama and Open Web UI</strong></p><p>One of the most exciting takeaways from DevFest was the potential of running LLMs locally. Tools like <strong>Ollama</strong> (<a href="https://ollama.com/">https://ollama.com/</a>) and <strong>Open Web UI</strong> (<a href="https://docs.openwebui.com/">https://docs.openwebui.com/</a>) make it surprisingly easy to experiment with LLMs on your machine, opening up a world of possibilities for privacy-preserving AI projects.</p><p><strong>More DevFest discoveries</strong></p><p>DevFest London also introduced me to some promising tools and platforms:</p><ul><li><strong>Codemagic:</strong> (<a href="https://codemagic.io/start/">https://codemagic.io/start/</a>) A CI/CD platform for mobile app development.</li><li><strong>Flutterflow:</strong> (<a href="https://www.flutterflow.io/">https://www.flutterflow.io/</a>) A low-code platform for building Flutter apps.</li></ul><p><strong>My robotic endeavor 😂</strong></p><p>I even attempted to build a robot! You can see the results in the GIF below.</p><figure><img alt="This robot is coming to life, one Lego brick at a time" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/500/1*6HFOcVrsg4lBP9gGhtQYPw.gif" /><figcaption>This robot is coming to life, one Lego brick at a time</figcaption></figure><p><strong>Final thoughts</strong></p><p>DevFest London 2024 was a whirlwind of AI innovation, insightful discussions, and inspiring connections. These passionate developers and forward-thinking companies are clearly shaping the future of technology. I can’t wait to see what next year’s event holds.</p><figure><img alt="Great memories with fellow attendees at DevFest London 2024!" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*FCWoqDvG2t8Cxsf6" /><figcaption>Great memories with fellow attendees at DevFest London 2024!</figcaption></figure><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=edbe51970066" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="google-developer-group" /><category term="devfest-2024" /><category term="devfest-london" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have attended DevFest events around the globe — from India to Sweden, Norway, and the UK. DevFest London was a standout experience this year, buzzing with the energy of 28 speakers, 4 tracks, and over 260 attendees.A close-up of the DevFest London 2024 attendee badgeHaving previously presented on cloud, data, AI platforms, and responsible AI in Stockholm and India, I was naturally drawn to the AI track. The sessions were a fascinating exploration of cutting-edge topics, ranging from:Generative AI model performance: A deep dive into the capabilities and limitations of today’s most advanced AI models.Prompt injection attacks: A critical look at the security vulnerabilities of LLMs and how to mitigate them.Avoiding common LLM pitfalls: Practical advice on navigating the challenges of working with large language models.The rise of LVMs: Insights into why Large Vision Models are poised to revolutionize how we interact with visual data.Harnessing the power of Gemini: Expert tips on leveraging Google’s latest AI model while staying within ethical boundaries.AutoML with Vertex AI: Empowering business users to build and deploy machine learning models without coding expertise.Google’s Secure AI Framework (SAIF): A comprehensive overview of Google’s approach to building secure and trustworthy AI systems.Banner displaying the logos of companies sponsoring DevFest London 2024My DevFest secret weapon: granola.aiIn the whirlwind of back-to-back sessions, I discovered a game-changer: granola.ai. This incredible tool transcribed the sessions in real-time, allowing me to fully engage with the presentations without worrying about taking notes. If you’re a meeting maestro juggling a packed schedule, granola.ai is your new best friend.Taking LLMs offline with Ollama and Open Web UIOne of the most exciting takeaways from DevFest was the potential of running LLMs locally. Tools like Ollama (https://ollama.com/) and Open Web UI (https://docs.openwebui.com/) make it surprisingly easy to experiment with LLMs on your machine, opening up a world of possibilities for privacy-preserving AI projects.More DevFest discoveriesDevFest London also introduced me to some promising tools and platforms:Codemagic: (https://codemagic.io/start/) A CI/CD platform for mobile app development.Flutterflow: (https://www.flutterflow.io/) A low-code platform for building Flutter apps.My robotic endeavor 😂I even attempted to build a robot! You can see the results in the GIF below.This robot is coming to life, one Lego brick at a timeFinal thoughtsDevFest London 2024 was a whirlwind of AI innovation, insightful discussions, and inspiring connections. These passionate developers and forward-thinking companies are clearly shaping the future of technology. I can’t wait to see what next year’s event holds.Great memories with fellow attendees at DevFest London 2024!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My unexpected coffee love affair: The eggnog latte</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/15/my-unexpected-coffee-love-affair-the-eggnog-latte.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My unexpected coffee love affair: The eggnog latte" /><published>2024-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/15/my-unexpected-coffee-love-affair-the-eggnog-latte</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/15/my-unexpected-coffee-love-affair-the-eggnog-latte.html"><![CDATA[<p>For years, I’ve travelled the world, exploring new cultures and cuisines, and sharing my experiences through my posts on Instagram. From bustling markets in India to Michelin-starred restaurants in Sweden, I’ve savoured a vast array of flavours. But one thing I’ve kept surprisingly quiet about is my love for coffee. It might seem mundane compared to my more exotic culinary adventures, but coffee has become an essential part of my daily ritual.</p><figure><img alt="The warmth of an eggnog latte brightened a chilly London afternoon." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*NO1w7TF-3kXpghhdC_9--g.jpeg" /><figcaption>The warmth of an eggnog latte brightened a chilly London afternoon.</figcaption></figure><p>My coffee journey began with simple instant coffee lovingly prepared by my mother, a taste I preferred as a child. Over time, my preferences evolved, leading me to discover the bold flavours of Indian filter coffee and the comforting warmth of a European latte.</p><p>I’ve always been a creature of habit, frequenting the same cafes in each city I’ve lived in. But it was in London, with its vibrant cafe culture, that I truly expanded my coffee horizons. From cosy independent shops to bustling chains, I’ve become a regular at them all.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*NpsDAWRnWFxy_bFHBgkAwA.jpeg" /><figcaption>A Parisian cafe latte</figcaption></figure><p>Which brings me to the star of today’s post: the <strong>Eggnog Latte</strong>. Now, I’ll admit, the concept of eggs in my coffee was initially a bit jarring. But curiosity got the better of me, and I decided to give this festive concoction a try.</p><h4><strong>A Brief History of Eggnog</strong></h4><p>Before we dive into the latte itself, let’s take a quick trip back in time. Eggnog, with its rich and creamy texture, has a surprisingly long history. It originated from a medieval British hot milk drink called “posset,” eventually making its way to the American colonies where it became a Christmas staple. Today, variations of eggnog are enjoyed globally, from “rompope” in Mexico to “coquito” in Puerto Rico.</p><figure><img alt="Sipping instant coffee amidst the cool air of the hill station" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*Wf6gMGxOtKTMuunAP451TQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>Sipping instant coffee amidst the cool air of the hill station</figcaption></figure><h4><strong>What Exactly is Eggnog?</strong></h4><p>Essentially, eggnog is a decadent blend of milk, cream, sugar, eggs, and warming spices like nutmeg and cinnamon. Often, a splash of alcohol like rum, brandy, or bourbon is added for an extra layer of festive cheer.</p><h4><strong>Making Eggnog from Scratch</strong></h4><p>If you’re feeling adventurous, here’s a simplified version of how this holiday treat is made:</p><ol><li><strong>Infuse the milk:</strong> Gently heat milk with spices like cinnamon and cloves.</li><li><strong>Create the base:</strong> Whisk egg yolks and sugar until light and fluffy.</li><li><strong>Temper the eggs:</strong> Gradually add the warm milk to the egg yolks, whisking constantly to prevent curdling.</li><li><strong>Thicken the mixture:</strong> Cook over low heat until it reaches a custard-like consistency.</li><li><strong>Chill:</strong> Allow the eggnog to cool completely.</li><li><strong>Add alcohol (optional):</strong> Stir in your preferred spirit.</li><li><strong>Lighten it up (optional):</strong> Fold in whipped egg whites for extra airiness.</li></ol><h4><strong>Important Notes:</strong></h4><ul><li><strong>Safety first:</strong> Always use pasteurized eggs to avoid any risk of salmonella.</li><li><strong>Variety is the spice of life:</strong> Experiment with different spices, alcohol, and flavourings to create your perfect eggnog.</li><li><strong>Store it right:</strong> Homemade eggnog can be kept in the fridge for several days.</li></ul><figure><img alt="The taste of Chennai: filter coffee, flawlessly brewed" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*jBErY2_J8P_DSbXmP3sK_g.jpeg" /><figcaption>The taste of Chennai: filter coffee, flawlessly brewed</figcaption></figure><p>Whether you’re a seasoned coffee lover or just looking to try something new, the eggnog latte is a delicious way to embrace the holiday spirit. So go ahead, treat yourself to this festive indulgence — you won’t regret it!</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=aeeb5b758928" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cafe" /><category term="coffee-culture" /><category term="london" /><category term="coffee" /><category term="eggnog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For years, I’ve travelled the world, exploring new cultures and cuisines, and sharing my experiences through my posts on Instagram. From bustling markets in India to Michelin-starred restaurants in Sweden, I’ve savoured a vast array of flavours. But one thing I’ve kept surprisingly quiet about is my love for coffee. It might seem mundane compared to my more exotic culinary adventures, but coffee has become an essential part of my daily ritual.The warmth of an eggnog latte brightened a chilly London afternoon.My coffee journey began with simple instant coffee lovingly prepared by my mother, a taste I preferred as a child. Over time, my preferences evolved, leading me to discover the bold flavours of Indian filter coffee and the comforting warmth of a European latte.I’ve always been a creature of habit, frequenting the same cafes in each city I’ve lived in. But it was in London, with its vibrant cafe culture, that I truly expanded my coffee horizons. From cosy independent shops to bustling chains, I’ve become a regular at them all.A Parisian cafe latteWhich brings me to the star of today’s post: the Eggnog Latte. Now, I’ll admit, the concept of eggs in my coffee was initially a bit jarring. But curiosity got the better of me, and I decided to give this festive concoction a try.A Brief History of EggnogBefore we dive into the latte itself, let’s take a quick trip back in time. Eggnog, with its rich and creamy texture, has a surprisingly long history. It originated from a medieval British hot milk drink called “posset,” eventually making its way to the American colonies where it became a Christmas staple. Today, variations of eggnog are enjoyed globally, from “rompope” in Mexico to “coquito” in Puerto Rico.Sipping instant coffee amidst the cool air of the hill stationWhat Exactly is Eggnog?Essentially, eggnog is a decadent blend of milk, cream, sugar, eggs, and warming spices like nutmeg and cinnamon. Often, a splash of alcohol like rum, brandy, or bourbon is added for an extra layer of festive cheer.Making Eggnog from ScratchIf you’re feeling adventurous, here’s a simplified version of how this holiday treat is made:Infuse the milk: Gently heat milk with spices like cinnamon and cloves.Create the base: Whisk egg yolks and sugar until light and fluffy.Temper the eggs: Gradually add the warm milk to the egg yolks, whisking constantly to prevent curdling.Thicken the mixture: Cook over low heat until it reaches a custard-like consistency.Chill: Allow the eggnog to cool completely.Add alcohol (optional): Stir in your preferred spirit.Lighten it up (optional): Fold in whipped egg whites for extra airiness.Important Notes:Safety first: Always use pasteurized eggs to avoid any risk of salmonella.Variety is the spice of life: Experiment with different spices, alcohol, and flavourings to create your perfect eggnog.Store it right: Homemade eggnog can be kept in the fridge for several days.The taste of Chennai: filter coffee, flawlessly brewedWhether you’re a seasoned coffee lover or just looking to try something new, the eggnog latte is a delicious way to embrace the holiday spirit. So go ahead, treat yourself to this festive indulgence — you won’t regret it!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">More than just a game: Ping Pong Diplomacy and the Wisdom of Losing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/06/more-than-just-a-game-ping-pong-diplomacy-and-the-wisdom-of-losing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More than just a game: Ping Pong Diplomacy and the Wisdom of Losing" /><published>2024-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/06/more-than-just-a-game-ping-pong-diplomacy-and-the-wisdom-of-losing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/06/more-than-just-a-game-ping-pong-diplomacy-and-the-wisdom-of-losing.html"><![CDATA[<p>Ping pong, or table tennis as it’s formally known, has a surprisingly rich history. Born from Victorian England’s high society as an after-dinner amusement, it quickly evolved from improvised games with book “nets” and champagne-cork “balls” to a globally recognised sport. But beyond the paddles and the celluloid balls lies a fascinating tale of international relations — ping-pong diplomacy.</p><figure><img alt="A photo of a ping pong championship at the H&amp;M Group office in Stockholm in 2021" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*p-j4OFGxFeyHyIAzzUKxNg.png" /><figcaption>A photo of a ping-pong championship at the H&amp;M Group office in Stockholm in 2021</figcaption></figure><p>This unlikely diplomatic tool emerged in the early 1970s, amidst the Cold War’s icy grip. An exchange of table tennis players between the US and China thawed the frozen tension, paving the way for President Nixon’s historic visit to China in 1972. Who knew that a seemingly simple game could hold such geopolitical power?</p><p>But ping-pong diplomacy is more than just a historical footnote. It speaks to the deeper human capacity for connection and understanding, even across seemingly insurmountable divides. And this is where Japan enters the story.</p><p>In his insightful TED Talk, Pico Iyer explores the unique philosophy surrounding ping pong in Japan. He observes a culture that fosters a competitive spirit without the cutthroat edge we often see in the West. It’s a subtle distinction, but one that reveals a profound wisdom: losing isn’t the opposite of winning; it’s failing to see the bigger picture.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fembed.ted.com%2Ftalks%2Fpico_iyer_the_beauty_of_what_we_ll_never_know&amp;display_name=TED&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.ted.com%2Ftalks%2Fpico_iyer_the_beauty_of_what_we_ll_never_know&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fpi.tedcdn.com%2Fr%2Ftalkstar-photos.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fuploads%2Fb4e0ae64-7e9a-4aa3-ad5c-19d6c29d7b53%2FPicoIyer_2016T-embed.jpg%3Fh%3D316%26w%3D560&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=ted" width="560" height="316" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/2f9b181f613328e52002e49f665000be/href">https://medium.com/media/2f9b181f613328e52002e49f665000be/href</a></iframe><p>This resonated with me deeply. I’ve learned that true success lies not just in achieving victory, but in understanding the journey, the lessons learned, and the connections forged along the way.</p><p>Pico Iyer’s observations on ping-pong in Japan offer a valuable lesson for us all. In a world obsessed with winning, perhaps we need to embrace a new perspective. Perhaps, like the Japanese ping-pong players, we need to find the competitive spirit within ourselves, without losing sight of the shared humanity that connects us all.</p><figure><img alt="A festive scene of Stockholm’s Skansen market at Christmas time" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*evhtlXTN09niSp1gvZDEow.jpeg" /><figcaption>A festive scene of Stockholm’s Skansen market at Christmas time</figcaption></figure><p>So the next time you pick up a paddle, remember that ping-pong is more than just a game. It’s a microcosm of human interaction, a testament to the power of connection, and a reminder that sometimes, losing can be the greatest win of all.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=b0ccb584ce5b" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="table-tennis" /><category term="life-lessons" /><category term="ping-pong-diplomacy" /><category term="self-awareness" /><category term="self-improvement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ping pong, or table tennis as it’s formally known, has a surprisingly rich history. Born from Victorian England’s high society as an after-dinner amusement, it quickly evolved from improvised games with book “nets” and champagne-cork “balls” to a globally recognised sport. But beyond the paddles and the celluloid balls lies a fascinating tale of international relations — ping-pong diplomacy.A photo of a ping-pong championship at the H&amp;M Group office in Stockholm in 2021This unlikely diplomatic tool emerged in the early 1970s, amidst the Cold War’s icy grip. An exchange of table tennis players between the US and China thawed the frozen tension, paving the way for President Nixon’s historic visit to China in 1972. Who knew that a seemingly simple game could hold such geopolitical power?But ping-pong diplomacy is more than just a historical footnote. It speaks to the deeper human capacity for connection and understanding, even across seemingly insurmountable divides. And this is where Japan enters the story.In his insightful TED Talk, Pico Iyer explores the unique philosophy surrounding ping pong in Japan. He observes a culture that fosters a competitive spirit without the cutthroat edge we often see in the West. It’s a subtle distinction, but one that reveals a profound wisdom: losing isn’t the opposite of winning; it’s failing to see the bigger picture.https://medium.com/media/2f9b181f613328e52002e49f665000be/hrefThis resonated with me deeply. I’ve learned that true success lies not just in achieving victory, but in understanding the journey, the lessons learned, and the connections forged along the way.Pico Iyer’s observations on ping-pong in Japan offer a valuable lesson for us all. In a world obsessed with winning, perhaps we need to embrace a new perspective. Perhaps, like the Japanese ping-pong players, we need to find the competitive spirit within ourselves, without losing sight of the shared humanity that connects us all.A festive scene of Stockholm’s Skansen market at Christmas timeSo the next time you pick up a paddle, remember that ping-pong is more than just a game. It’s a microcosm of human interaction, a testament to the power of connection, and a reminder that sometimes, losing can be the greatest win of all.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond the Classroom: How student tech programs shaped my journey</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/beyond-the-classroom-how-student-tech-programs-shaped-my-journey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond the Classroom: How student tech programs shaped my journey" /><published>2024-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/beyond-the-classroom-how-student-tech-programs-shaped-my-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/beyond-the-classroom-how-student-tech-programs-shaped-my-journey.html"><![CDATA[<p>As a curious individual, my journey in technology began in the 2010s thanks to student technology programs. Programs like Microsoft Student Partner, Github Education Program, and Google Student Ambassador were eye-opening experiences for me and my peers. During my time pursuing a Bachelor’s in Computer Science and Engineering at Anna University, through M. Kumarasamy College of Engineering in Karur, I had the freedom to engage in various tech programs and communities. This journey led me to inaugurate and build tech communities within the college.</p><p>My involvement in multiple technology communities, starting with the Microsoft Student Program and the Google Developers Group Chapter in Coimbatore, introduced me to the world of open source and cloud engineering. I had opportunities to learn, experiment, build, and educate others on modern tech stacks. These experiences opened doors to internships at various organisations and participation in events organised by companies like Microsoft, Google, Tata Consultancy Services, Wipro, Dell, and others.</p><figure><img alt="A narrow, serene street in Stockholm with historic buildings and a distant church dome framed by autumn trees." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*03GPRq_YHAIppv0lbZHtWQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>A narrow, serene street in Stockholm with historic buildings and a distant church dome framed by autumn trees.</figcaption></figure><h4><strong>Through my active participation in technical associations and communities, I gained valuable hard and soft skills. </strong>Some of the most important lessons learned include,</h4><p><strong>Communication and Collaboration:</strong> Community involvement necessitates active participation in diverse activities. This includes marketing events, organising tech fests, coordinating with volunteers to conduct workshops and community-driven events, advocating for technology and tech-led products, securing sponsorships, and engaging in speaking opportunities at various forums and hackathons. Effective communication is crucial for clearly conveying ideas and ensuring successful execution. The collaboration further enhances workflows and outcomes.</p><p><strong>Decision Making:</strong> Every piece of information received or created presents an opportunity for decision-making. In tech communities, decisions are made daily, ranging from event planning, securing sponsorships, and successfully executing events to gathering feedback and making improvements.</p><p><strong>Delivering Value:</strong> The transformative nature of the tech industry requires communities to stay abreast of the latest releases and manage change effectively. This experience taught me valuable lessons in change management, future planning, risk mitigation, navigating challenges, and continuously updating my skills to achieve success.</p><p><strong>Program and Project Management:</strong> Being part of a community extends beyond simply delivering value; it involves learning about program management and tackling real-life problems to maintain momentum and inspire fellow students to participate in the tech world and foster innovation. This provided opportunities to learn project management using tools like Jira, Confluence for documentation, Trello, and Notion, all of which offer free versions for students.</p><figure><img alt="A crowd gathers beneath the famous Prague Astronomical Clock on a clear day, admiring the intricate details of the historic tower." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*BVU92xC2LMY_NRsUmn9hsQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>A crowd gathers beneath the famous Prague Astronomical Clock on a clear day, admiring the intricate details of the historic tower.</figcaption></figure><p><strong>Delegation:</strong> Understanding the nature of work and prioritising tasks based on importance and time sensitivity are essential for achieving optimal outcomes. Delegating tasks to fellow community members allows for skill development while enabling focus on critical tasks and enhancing overall productivity.</p><p><strong>Leadership:</strong> Effectively managing and leading communities requires strong leadership skills. A leader inspires fellow members through their work ethic and indirectly influences them to adopt their approach. Key leadership qualities include empathy, honest feedback, mentorship, leading by example, and providing support for task completion.</p><p><strong>Technology Toolbox:</strong> Like a mechanic’s toolbox, a technology toolbox is essential for success. This toolbox should include productivity tools, such as Microsoft Office or Google Workspace, as well as project and product management tools. Essential development tools include, but are not limited to, programming languages like Java, Python, React, JS, and other relevant frameworks. Low-code and no-code tools for business enthusiasts, design and graphics engineering tools for designers, testing tools for testing engineers, network and security tools, and cloud and AI technologies are also crucial for success.</p><h4>Technology companies often recognise the potential of the future workforce and offer free licenses and tools for students to build, test, and experiment with their products and services.</h4><h4>Some of them are listed below, research on this topic to get more benefits.</h4><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/education">GitHub Education</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/kamath/student-free-stuff">GitHub - kamath/student-free-stuff: Just a list of free software dev tools students can get</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/AchoArnold/discount-for-student-dev">GitHub - AchoArnold/discount-for-student-dev: This is list of discounts on software (SaaS, PaaS, IaaS, etc.) and other offerings for developers who are students</a></li></ul><p>These lessons learned from being a part of student tech communities have been invaluable in shaping my career and personal growth. I encourage all aspiring technologists to actively engage in these communities to foster their development and contribute to the ever-evolving world of technology.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=d6b3e604dae6" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="engineering-students" /><category term="microsoft-student-partner" /><category term="student-societies" /><category term="google-developer-group" /><category term="technology-community" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a curious individual, my journey in technology began in the 2010s thanks to student technology programs. Programs like Microsoft Student Partner, Github Education Program, and Google Student Ambassador were eye-opening experiences for me and my peers. During my time pursuing a Bachelor’s in Computer Science and Engineering at Anna University, through M. Kumarasamy College of Engineering in Karur, I had the freedom to engage in various tech programs and communities. This journey led me to inaugurate and build tech communities within the college.My involvement in multiple technology communities, starting with the Microsoft Student Program and the Google Developers Group Chapter in Coimbatore, introduced me to the world of open source and cloud engineering. I had opportunities to learn, experiment, build, and educate others on modern tech stacks. These experiences opened doors to internships at various organisations and participation in events organised by companies like Microsoft, Google, Tata Consultancy Services, Wipro, Dell, and others.A narrow, serene street in Stockholm with historic buildings and a distant church dome framed by autumn trees.Through my active participation in technical associations and communities, I gained valuable hard and soft skills. Some of the most important lessons learned include,Communication and Collaboration: Community involvement necessitates active participation in diverse activities. This includes marketing events, organising tech fests, coordinating with volunteers to conduct workshops and community-driven events, advocating for technology and tech-led products, securing sponsorships, and engaging in speaking opportunities at various forums and hackathons. Effective communication is crucial for clearly conveying ideas and ensuring successful execution. The collaboration further enhances workflows and outcomes.Decision Making: Every piece of information received or created presents an opportunity for decision-making. In tech communities, decisions are made daily, ranging from event planning, securing sponsorships, and successfully executing events to gathering feedback and making improvements.Delivering Value: The transformative nature of the tech industry requires communities to stay abreast of the latest releases and manage change effectively. This experience taught me valuable lessons in change management, future planning, risk mitigation, navigating challenges, and continuously updating my skills to achieve success.Program and Project Management: Being part of a community extends beyond simply delivering value; it involves learning about program management and tackling real-life problems to maintain momentum and inspire fellow students to participate in the tech world and foster innovation. This provided opportunities to learn project management using tools like Jira, Confluence for documentation, Trello, and Notion, all of which offer free versions for students.A crowd gathers beneath the famous Prague Astronomical Clock on a clear day, admiring the intricate details of the historic tower.Delegation: Understanding the nature of work and prioritising tasks based on importance and time sensitivity are essential for achieving optimal outcomes. Delegating tasks to fellow community members allows for skill development while enabling focus on critical tasks and enhancing overall productivity.Leadership: Effectively managing and leading communities requires strong leadership skills. A leader inspires fellow members through their work ethic and indirectly influences them to adopt their approach. Key leadership qualities include empathy, honest feedback, mentorship, leading by example, and providing support for task completion.Technology Toolbox: Like a mechanic’s toolbox, a technology toolbox is essential for success. This toolbox should include productivity tools, such as Microsoft Office or Google Workspace, as well as project and product management tools. Essential development tools include, but are not limited to, programming languages like Java, Python, React, JS, and other relevant frameworks. Low-code and no-code tools for business enthusiasts, design and graphics engineering tools for designers, testing tools for testing engineers, network and security tools, and cloud and AI technologies are also crucial for success.Technology companies often recognise the potential of the future workforce and offer free licenses and tools for students to build, test, and experiment with their products and services.Some of them are listed below, research on this topic to get more benefits.GitHub EducationGitHub - kamath/student-free-stuff: Just a list of free software dev tools students can getGitHub - AchoArnold/discount-for-student-dev: This is list of discounts on software (SaaS, PaaS, IaaS, etc.) and other offerings for developers who are studentsThese lessons learned from being a part of student tech communities have been invaluable in shaping my career and personal growth. I encourage all aspiring technologists to actively engage in these communities to foster their development and contribute to the ever-evolving world of technology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Investing in Customer Reliability: Why it matters for Cloud Providers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/27/investing-in-customer-reliability-why-it-matters-for-cloud-providers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investing in Customer Reliability: Why it matters for Cloud Providers" /><published>2024-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/27/investing-in-customer-reliability-why-it-matters-for-cloud-providers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/27/investing-in-customer-reliability-why-it-matters-for-cloud-providers.html"><![CDATA[<p>In today’s digital landscape, reliability is paramount, especially for businesses reliant on cloud services. Cloud providers like Google Cloud understand this and are increasingly investing in <strong>Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE)</strong>. But what’s in it for them? Why empower customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability? Let’s explore the compelling reasons behind this trend.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*b4O92EM8pcC-2jNaTw48rA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Two people in cosy sweaters serve “Varm Glögg” from a festive, snow-topped wooden stall at a Christmas market in Stockholm, illuminated by warm lights.</figcaption></figure><h4>Time to learn about Glögg 🍷</h4><p>Glögg is a Swedish word, that refers to the traditional Scandinavian mulled wine, typically served warm during the winter months and Christmas season. It’s spiced with cinnamon, cloves, cardamom, and often served with almonds and raisins, offering a cosy, festive flavour.</p><p>Shifting our focus back, cloud providers are investing in customer reliability engineering for the following reasons</p><h4><strong>Reliability breeds trust and loyalty</strong></h4><p>For cloud vendors, a reliable service is the bedrock of customer trust. When businesses entrust their critical operations to a cloud provider, they expect consistent uptime and minimal disruptions. By investing in CRE and providing customers with the tools and knowledge to manage their own reliability, cloud vendors foster a sense of partnership and confidence. This, in turn, translates to increased customer loyalty and long-term relationships.</p><h4><strong>Shared responsibility, shared success</strong></h4><p>Cloud computing thrives on a shared responsibility model. While providers are responsible for the underlying infrastructure, customers play a crucial role in building and managing reliable applications on top of that infrastructure. By empowering customers with CRE principles and practices, cloud vendors enable them to take ownership of their reliability, leading to a more stable and successful ecosystem for all involved.</p><h4><strong>Reducing downtime costs</strong></h4><p>Downtime can be incredibly expensive for businesses, leading to lost revenue, damaged reputation, and recovery efforts. By proactively addressing reliability concerns and equipping customers to manage their systems effectively, cloud vendors contribute to minimising potential downtime risks. This proactive approach reduces the likelihood of costly outages for both the customer and the provider.</p><h4><strong>Unlocking business value through stability</strong></h4><p>When businesses can rely on the stability of their cloud environments, they are free to innovate and focus on their core competencies. CRE empowers customers to build mission-critical teams that can ensure the smooth operation of their applications, allowing them to leverage the full potential of the cloud without being bogged down by reliability concerns</p><h4><strong>A culture of continuous improvement</strong></h4><p>Investing in CRE fosters a culture of continuous improvement within both the cloud provider and the customer’s organisation. By embracing principles like blameless postmortems and proactive monitoring, both parties can identify areas for optimisation and continuously enhance the reliability of their systems.</p><p>In conclusion, cloud providers are investing in <strong>Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE)</strong> because it’s a strategic imperative in today’s competitive market. By empowering customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability, they’re not just selling services, they’re building long-term partnerships based on trust, shared success, and a commitment to delivering exceptional digital experiences.</p><h4>Reference:</h4><p><a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/devops-sre/introducing-a-new-era-of-customer-support-google-customer-reliability-engineering">Introducing Google Customer Reliability Engineering | Google Cloud Blog</a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=30d23c1fb0f7" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cloud-partnerships" /><category term="cloud-computing" /><category term="customer-experience" /><category term="reliability-engineering" /><category term="google-cloud-platform" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In today’s digital landscape, reliability is paramount, especially for businesses reliant on cloud services. Cloud providers like Google Cloud understand this and are increasingly investing in Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE). But what’s in it for them? Why empower customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability? Let’s explore the compelling reasons behind this trend.Two people in cosy sweaters serve “Varm Glögg” from a festive, snow-topped wooden stall at a Christmas market in Stockholm, illuminated by warm lights.Time to learn about Glögg 🍷Glögg is a Swedish word, that refers to the traditional Scandinavian mulled wine, typically served warm during the winter months and Christmas season. It’s spiced with cinnamon, cloves, cardamom, and often served with almonds and raisins, offering a cosy, festive flavour.Shifting our focus back, cloud providers are investing in customer reliability engineering for the following reasonsReliability breeds trust and loyaltyFor cloud vendors, a reliable service is the bedrock of customer trust. When businesses entrust their critical operations to a cloud provider, they expect consistent uptime and minimal disruptions. By investing in CRE and providing customers with the tools and knowledge to manage their own reliability, cloud vendors foster a sense of partnership and confidence. This, in turn, translates to increased customer loyalty and long-term relationships.Shared responsibility, shared successCloud computing thrives on a shared responsibility model. While providers are responsible for the underlying infrastructure, customers play a crucial role in building and managing reliable applications on top of that infrastructure. By empowering customers with CRE principles and practices, cloud vendors enable them to take ownership of their reliability, leading to a more stable and successful ecosystem for all involved.Reducing downtime costsDowntime can be incredibly expensive for businesses, leading to lost revenue, damaged reputation, and recovery efforts. By proactively addressing reliability concerns and equipping customers to manage their systems effectively, cloud vendors contribute to minimising potential downtime risks. This proactive approach reduces the likelihood of costly outages for both the customer and the provider.Unlocking business value through stabilityWhen businesses can rely on the stability of their cloud environments, they are free to innovate and focus on their core competencies. CRE empowers customers to build mission-critical teams that can ensure the smooth operation of their applications, allowing them to leverage the full potential of the cloud without being bogged down by reliability concernsA culture of continuous improvementInvesting in CRE fosters a culture of continuous improvement within both the cloud provider and the customer’s organisation. By embracing principles like blameless postmortems and proactive monitoring, both parties can identify areas for optimisation and continuously enhance the reliability of their systems.In conclusion, cloud providers are investing in Customer Reliability Engineering (CRE) because it’s a strategic imperative in today’s competitive market. By empowering customers to build mission-critical teams focused on reliability, they’re not just selling services, they’re building long-term partnerships based on trust, shared success, and a commitment to delivering exceptional digital experiences.Reference:Introducing Google Customer Reliability Engineering | Google Cloud Blog]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google’s Gemini at Work: Data is the key</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/26/google-s-gemini-at-work-data-is-the-key.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google’s Gemini at Work: Data is the key" /><published>2024-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/26/google-s-gemini-at-work-data-is-the-key</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/26/google-s-gemini-at-work-data-is-the-key.html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday’s “Gemini at Work Live” event showcased Google’s latest AI advancements, emphasizing how <strong>data is crucial for unlocking AI’s potential</strong>. While “foundation models” are powerful, the event stressed that they alone aren’t enough. Businesses need a holistic strategy to prepare data, choose the right models, and seamlessly integrate them into their systems. This is where Google’s offerings shine.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*j2n3NOmkwgVkUQTKTjEDig.png" /><figcaption>Statue of Birger Jarl at Riddarholmen in Stockholm</figcaption></figure><h3>Gemini: More Than Just Models</h3><p>The event highlighted Gemini’s capabilities beyond basic AI models. Here are some key takeaways:</p><p><strong>Customer-Centric Solutions:</strong> Gemini is revolutionising customer service with intelligent agents. Imagine agents that not only understand complex requests but also provide personalised experiences.</p><p><strong>Boosting Workplace Efficiency:</strong> Gemini is set to redefine productivity. Employee agents will streamline tasks, offer instant information access, and make workflows incredibly smooth.</p><p><strong>Data at Your Fingertips:</strong> Features like Vertex AI Search, powered by Google’s renowned search technology, will allow businesses to extract invaluable insights from their data.</p><p><strong>Looker Gets Smarter:</strong> With Gemini, Looker becomes even more powerful. Conversational analytics allows users to interact with data using natural language, get AI-driven suggestions, and visualise insights effortlessly.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FqmIZyPJgRiI%3Ffeature%3Doembed&amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DqmIZyPJgRiI&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FqmIZyPJgRiI%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/efd9b486dddfa7bc46098b4925b80f2c/href">https://medium.com/media/efd9b486dddfa7bc46098b4925b80f2c/href</a></iframe><h3>BigQuery: The Data Powerhouse</h3><p>The event positioned BigQuery as the cornerstone of this AI revolution. Here’s why:</p><p><strong>Unified Engine:</strong> BigQuery’s new unified engine ensures high performance and seamless management, making it ideal for handling the demands of AI workloads.</p><p><strong>Unified Storage:</strong> BigQuery is designed to handle various data types (multimodal data), a crucial aspect of today’s diverse data landscape.</p><p><strong>Built-in AI:</strong> With BigQuery ML and other integration capabilities, BigQuery emerges as a comprehensive platform for AI solutions.</p><h3>Finally Google’s AI Advantage</h3><p>The event strongly emphasized Google Cloud’s unified tech stack as a significant advantage.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*WAn3EVhBqnxdQevBOW0WDw.png" /><figcaption>Google Cloud’s AI Optimised Stack</figcaption></figure><p><strong>AI Hypercomputer:</strong> This forms the foundation for Google’s AI prowess.</p><p><strong>Vertex AI:</strong> This serves as the platform for building and deploying AI models, including the powerful Model Garden.</p><p><strong>Gemini:</strong> This sits at the forefront, powering Google Cloud, Workspace, and specialised Agents.</p><p>The event presented a compelling case for businesses to view their data as a competitive advantage in the age of AI. Google Cloud, with its suite of integrated solutions like Gemini, Vertex AI, and BigQuery, offers a comprehensive pathway for businesses to harness their data’s full potential.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=8faf31a93774" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="google-cloud-platform" /><category term="vertex-ai" /><category term="bigquery" /><category term="google-gemini" /><category term="google-ai" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday’s “Gemini at Work Live” event showcased Google’s latest AI advancements, emphasizing how data is crucial for unlocking AI’s potential. While “foundation models” are powerful, the event stressed that they alone aren’t enough. Businesses need a holistic strategy to prepare data, choose the right models, and seamlessly integrate them into their systems. This is where Google’s offerings shine.Statue of Birger Jarl at Riddarholmen in StockholmGemini: More Than Just ModelsThe event highlighted Gemini’s capabilities beyond basic AI models. Here are some key takeaways:Customer-Centric Solutions: Gemini is revolutionising customer service with intelligent agents. Imagine agents that not only understand complex requests but also provide personalised experiences.Boosting Workplace Efficiency: Gemini is set to redefine productivity. Employee agents will streamline tasks, offer instant information access, and make workflows incredibly smooth.Data at Your Fingertips: Features like Vertex AI Search, powered by Google’s renowned search technology, will allow businesses to extract invaluable insights from their data.Looker Gets Smarter: With Gemini, Looker becomes even more powerful. Conversational analytics allows users to interact with data using natural language, get AI-driven suggestions, and visualise insights effortlessly.https://medium.com/media/efd9b486dddfa7bc46098b4925b80f2c/hrefBigQuery: The Data PowerhouseThe event positioned BigQuery as the cornerstone of this AI revolution. Here’s why:Unified Engine: BigQuery’s new unified engine ensures high performance and seamless management, making it ideal for handling the demands of AI workloads.Unified Storage: BigQuery is designed to handle various data types (multimodal data), a crucial aspect of today’s diverse data landscape.Built-in AI: With BigQuery ML and other integration capabilities, BigQuery emerges as a comprehensive platform for AI solutions.Finally Google’s AI AdvantageThe event strongly emphasized Google Cloud’s unified tech stack as a significant advantage.Google Cloud’s AI Optimised StackAI Hypercomputer: This forms the foundation for Google’s AI prowess.Vertex AI: This serves as the platform for building and deploying AI models, including the powerful Model Garden.Gemini: This sits at the forefront, powering Google Cloud, Workspace, and specialised Agents.The event presented a compelling case for businesses to view their data as a competitive advantage in the age of AI. Google Cloud, with its suite of integrated solutions like Gemini, Vertex AI, and BigQuery, offers a comprehensive pathway for businesses to harness their data’s full potential.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI Infrastructure business is a pricey endeavor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/17/ai-infrastructure-business-is-a-pricey-endeavor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Infrastructure business is a pricey endeavor" /><published>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/17/ai-infrastructure-business-is-a-pricey-endeavor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/17/ai-infrastructure-business-is-a-pricey-endeavor.html"><![CDATA[<p>While AI might seem magical, in the business world, it’s about automating tasks using machines that learn from data and real-world situations. Advancements in Natural Language Generation (NLG) have led to Large Language Models (LLMs) and their ongoing improvement.</p><h4><strong>The hidden workhorse: AI Infrastructure</strong></h4><p>Often overlooked is the crucial role of AI engineering. It involves managing the data that fuels AI models and ensures they deliver the expected results when prompted. Handling this data at scale requires a robust infrastructure for both data and AI engineering workloads. Imagine an iceberg; the visible tip represents the AI system, while the vast, hidden part is the supporting infrastructure.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*ClyDM1Ot9zsfPoUe6K_rlQ.png" /><figcaption>Iceberg and the AI Systems</figcaption></figure><p>It’s exciting to see how your hand-drawn iceberg floats in real life. Thanks to Sketchplanations for introducing me to Iceberger, where you can create your iceberg and watch it float. Give it a try and be a kid again!</p><p><a href="https://joshdata.me/iceberger.html">Iceberger</a></p><h4>Why starting an AI Infrastructure company now might be tough</h4><p>This section doesn’t discuss the basics of building infrastructure or AI systems. However, venturing into AI infrastructure right now might not be ideal. Here’s a realistic perspective based on experiences within the AI ecosystem:</p><p><strong>Limited Market for Niche Solutions: </strong>Imagine starting a business to support a single vendor needing custom infrastructure for on-premise LLMs. This approach might not attract many future customers.</p><p><strong>Challenges in a Competitive Landscape:</strong> The existing market is competitive. Convincing customers to move away from established cloud vendors with their comprehensive governance, platforms, and tight integration is difficult.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*thvyZyIIbA4peuVSzCPIVA.jpeg" /><figcaption>The Grand Riksdag building (Sweden’s Parliament)</figcaption></figure><h4><strong>Key considerations for a successful AI Infrastructure startup</strong></h4><p>Here are some crucial aspects to consider for a future-proof AI infrastructure company:</p><ol><li><strong>Extensive research and development:</strong> Investing heavily in R&amp;D is essential to stay ahead of the curve and meet evolving customer needs.</li><li><strong>Technology stack:</strong> Innovating the right, scalable and flexible technology stack is crucial to accommodate current and future customer demands.</li><li><strong>Marketing and sales strategy:</strong> Develop a clear plan for marketing, sales communication, collaboration, and partnerships.</li><li><strong>Streamlined customer onboarding:</strong> Simplify the onboarding process, considering the fast-paced changes in the AI landscape.</li><li><strong>Predicting customer needs:</strong> Anticipate customer expectations to tailor your go-to-market strategy effectively.</li><li><strong>Focus on broader solutions:</strong> Instead of hyper-niche solutions, target broader problems affecting a wider range of customers.</li><li><strong>Understanding established players:</strong> Large companies have complex needs. A startup might not be able to solve all their problems, as changes in strategy and new product adoption can trigger internal changes and unique challenges.</li><li><strong>Cost optimization in a cloud-native world:</strong> Helping cloud-native customers find their sweet spot for cost savings and system efficiency is a significant challenge.</li><li><strong>Idea protection:</strong> While intellectual property theft is a concern, established companies can quickly adapt and implement innovative ideas.</li></ol><h4>Conclusion</h4><p>The AI infrastructure space is challenging but holds promise. Careful consideration of the market landscape and a well-defined strategy are crucial for success.</p><h4>Reference</h4><p>Iceberg Picture <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iceberg">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iceberg</a><br>Sketchplanations <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/iceberg-orientation">https://sketchplanations.com/iceberg-orientation</a><br>Iceberger <a href="https://joshdata.me/iceberger.html">https://joshdata.me/iceberger.html</a><br>Insights about AI Infrastructure startups <a href="https://nextword.substack.com/p/why-ai-infrastructure-startups-are">https://nextword.substack.com/p/why-ai-infrastructure-startups-are</a><br>Tools<a href="https://gemini.google.com/"> Google Gemini</a> for improvements and <a href="https://app.diagrams.net/">draw.io</a> for designing diagrams.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=5d2ba9812838" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-infrastructure-market" /><category term="ai-business" /><category term="ai-infrastructure" /><category term="ai" /><category term="ai-startups" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While AI might seem magical, in the business world, it’s about automating tasks using machines that learn from data and real-world situations. Advancements in Natural Language Generation (NLG) have led to Large Language Models (LLMs) and their ongoing improvement.The hidden workhorse: AI InfrastructureOften overlooked is the crucial role of AI engineering. It involves managing the data that fuels AI models and ensures they deliver the expected results when prompted. Handling this data at scale requires a robust infrastructure for both data and AI engineering workloads. Imagine an iceberg; the visible tip represents the AI system, while the vast, hidden part is the supporting infrastructure.Iceberg and the AI SystemsIt’s exciting to see how your hand-drawn iceberg floats in real life. Thanks to Sketchplanations for introducing me to Iceberger, where you can create your iceberg and watch it float. Give it a try and be a kid again!IcebergerWhy starting an AI Infrastructure company now might be toughThis section doesn’t discuss the basics of building infrastructure or AI systems. However, venturing into AI infrastructure right now might not be ideal. Here’s a realistic perspective based on experiences within the AI ecosystem:Limited Market for Niche Solutions: Imagine starting a business to support a single vendor needing custom infrastructure for on-premise LLMs. This approach might not attract many future customers.Challenges in a Competitive Landscape: The existing market is competitive. Convincing customers to move away from established cloud vendors with their comprehensive governance, platforms, and tight integration is difficult.The Grand Riksdag building (Sweden’s Parliament)Key considerations for a successful AI Infrastructure startupHere are some crucial aspects to consider for a future-proof AI infrastructure company:Extensive research and development: Investing heavily in R&amp;D is essential to stay ahead of the curve and meet evolving customer needs.Technology stack: Innovating the right, scalable and flexible technology stack is crucial to accommodate current and future customer demands.Marketing and sales strategy: Develop a clear plan for marketing, sales communication, collaboration, and partnerships.Streamlined customer onboarding: Simplify the onboarding process, considering the fast-paced changes in the AI landscape.Predicting customer needs: Anticipate customer expectations to tailor your go-to-market strategy effectively.Focus on broader solutions: Instead of hyper-niche solutions, target broader problems affecting a wider range of customers.Understanding established players: Large companies have complex needs. A startup might not be able to solve all their problems, as changes in strategy and new product adoption can trigger internal changes and unique challenges.Cost optimization in a cloud-native world: Helping cloud-native customers find their sweet spot for cost savings and system efficiency is a significant challenge.Idea protection: While intellectual property theft is a concern, established companies can quickly adapt and implement innovative ideas.ConclusionThe AI infrastructure space is challenging but holds promise. Careful consideration of the market landscape and a well-defined strategy are crucial for success.ReferenceIceberg Picture https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IcebergSketchplanations https://sketchplanations.com/iceberg-orientationIceberger https://joshdata.me/iceberger.htmlInsights about AI Infrastructure startups https://nextword.substack.com/p/why-ai-infrastructure-startups-areTools Google Gemini for improvements and draw.io for designing diagrams.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Podcast on Database Mastery: Insights from a Seasoned Engineer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/10/podcast-on-database-mastery-insights-from-a-seasoned-engineer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcast on Database Mastery: Insights from a Seasoned Engineer" /><published>2024-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/08/10/podcast-on-database-mastery-insights-from-a-seasoned-engineer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/10/podcast-on-database-mastery-insights-from-a-seasoned-engineer.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a habit of mine to share my thoughts on software engineering, real-world tech applications, and random musings on food, culture, and life experiences. Recently, I’ve dived deeper into podcasting, finding Spotify invaluable for distribution and Podcastle.ai a helpful tool for recording and post-production. I enjoy capturing insights from experienced individuals to share with others for their growth. To kick things off, I’ve collaborated with friends in the software industry to share their educational journeys, professional tips, and advice for early career professionals.</p><figure><img alt="Podcost Episode Cover Art" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*-PF8V92wJ1ZcTJuj8IiW1g.png" /><figcaption>Episode Cover Art</figcaption></figure><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fopen.spotify.com%2Fembed%2Fepisode%2F5r3EbJSUs3UwbNYRVgpg06%3Futm_source%3Doembed&amp;display_name=Spotify&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fopen.spotify.com%2Fepisode%2F5r3EbJSUs3UwbNYRVgpg06&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.scdn.co%2Fimage%2Fab67656300005f1f5e07eca04bfec1ce100a7c7c&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=spotify" width="456" height="152" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/d3730a02eda8b3f63fc43f2bda646db7/href">https://medium.com/media/d3730a02eda8b3f63fc43f2bda646db7/href</a></iframe><p>This episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.</p><p>This episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.</p><p>Packi’s LinkedIn Profile <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/packiyarajraja/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/packiyarajraja/</a></p><p>Packi boasts over a decade of experience working extensively with database and data engineering solutions, helping enterprises succeed worldwide. As a seasoned consultant for Fortune 500 companies, he excels at translating business needs into technical solutions.</p><figure><img alt="Kopparberg Cider" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*NgFPfF_LkL-e08RNkbPbhA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Kopparberg Cider</figcaption></figure><blockquote>Nothing beats the crisp refreshment of a cool cider on a warm summer day</blockquote><p>He emphasizes the importance of human collaboration, believing it’s crucial for personal growth. Success, for him, is built on trust with clients and stakeholders, leading to their satisfaction and ultimately, the company’s revenue.</p><p>He shares three pieces of advice for early career professionals:<br>1. Upgrade practical skills: Continuously enhance your abilities in programming, design, architecture, testing, analysis, etc.<br>2. Pursue your interests: Explore internships, freelancing, or open-source contributions that align with your passions.<br>3. Embrace AI: Incorporate AI into your toolkit to boost productivity.</p><p>Packi further elaborated on the impact of AI:</p><p>Before AI adoption: Highlight the traditional approach.<br>After AI adoption: Emphasize the potential for 100x productivity improvement through AI integration.</p><p>He concluded by stressing the significance of continuous learning, comparing it to fueling a car. He recommends dedicating at least 30 minutes daily to professional development.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*tkuK8GdPRgtGFSe_F8PZiA.jpeg" /><figcaption>A picture from our Yecaud trip. Lak, Packi and LP</figcaption></figure><p>I thank Packi for his time and valuable insights. And thanks LP(Lakshmipriya) for introducing Packi to me.</p><p>Thanks for taking the time to read this post.</p><p><strong>Follow my podcast channel for future episodes and your feedback is greatly appreciated.</strong></p><p><a href="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/lakshmikanth-rajamani">Insights from the Experienced * A podcast on Spotify for Podcasters</a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=4323c85bf901" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="database-engineer" /><category term="podcast" /><category term="database-development" /><category term="career-development" /><category term="career-advice" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s a habit of mine to share my thoughts on software engineering, real-world tech applications, and random musings on food, culture, and life experiences. Recently, I’ve dived deeper into podcasting, finding Spotify invaluable for distribution and Podcastle.ai a helpful tool for recording and post-production. I enjoy capturing insights from experienced individuals to share with others for their growth. To kick things off, I’ve collaborated with friends in the software industry to share their educational journeys, professional tips, and advice for early career professionals.Episode Cover Arthttps://medium.com/media/d3730a02eda8b3f63fc43f2bda646db7/hrefThis episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.This episode focuses on Database Mastery. I had the pleasure of interviewing my friend, Packi, to gain industry insights, learn essential tools for the professional toolkit, and learn about company expectations.Packi’s LinkedIn Profile https://www.linkedin.com/in/packiyarajraja/Packi boasts over a decade of experience working extensively with database and data engineering solutions, helping enterprises succeed worldwide. As a seasoned consultant for Fortune 500 companies, he excels at translating business needs into technical solutions.Kopparberg CiderNothing beats the crisp refreshment of a cool cider on a warm summer dayHe emphasizes the importance of human collaboration, believing it’s crucial for personal growth. Success, for him, is built on trust with clients and stakeholders, leading to their satisfaction and ultimately, the company’s revenue.He shares three pieces of advice for early career professionals:1. Upgrade practical skills: Continuously enhance your abilities in programming, design, architecture, testing, analysis, etc.2. Pursue your interests: Explore internships, freelancing, or open-source contributions that align with your passions.3. Embrace AI: Incorporate AI into your toolkit to boost productivity.Packi further elaborated on the impact of AI:Before AI adoption: Highlight the traditional approach.After AI adoption: Emphasize the potential for 100x productivity improvement through AI integration.He concluded by stressing the significance of continuous learning, comparing it to fueling a car. He recommends dedicating at least 30 minutes daily to professional development.A picture from our Yecaud trip. Lak, Packi and LPI thank Packi for his time and valuable insights. And thanks LP(Lakshmipriya) for introducing Packi to me.Thanks for taking the time to read this post.Follow my podcast channel for future episodes and your feedback is greatly appreciated.Insights from the Experienced * A podcast on Spotify for Podcasters]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Class SRE implements DevOps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/30/class-sre-implements-devops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Class SRE implements DevOps" /><published>2024-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/30/class-sre-implements-devops</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/30/class-sre-implements-devops.html"><![CDATA[<p>I am writing this blog post after taking a course from Google Cloud Boost Skills. It was fascinating to learn about the significance of SRE (Site Reliability Engineering) and DevOps in organizations of any size.</p><figure><img alt="Happy Lak is in Richmond Park, watching the deer." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*56Vs1J78eh9qhr3x435Klw.png" /><figcaption>Happy Lak is in Richmond Park, watching the deer.</figcaption></figure><p>Before diving into the importance of SRE and DevOps, let’s understand what DevOps is.</p><blockquote>Traditionally, developers and operators (the team that deploys and manages systems/applications) functioned in silos, leading to numerous challenges. This separation resulted in increased technical debt, longer time-to-market for solutions, and poor communication and collaboration between teams. Thanks to DevOps practices, teams are now structured in a more integrated manner to address both development and operational needs. This integrated approach reduces time-to-market with calculated risks, introducing terms such as SLA and SLI into the mix.</blockquote><p>SLA (Service Level Agreement): A commitment between a service provider and a client regarding the expected level of service</p><p>SLI (Service Level Indicator): A measure of the service level provided to the client</p><figure><img alt="A herd of deer is grazing in the park." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*Jp2UQNovFFZkbBaKaimUwQ.jpeg" /><figcaption>A herd of deer is grazing in the park.</figcaption></figure><p>Connecting five key touchpoints highlights the thin line between SRE and DevOps. Essentially, Class SRE implements DevOps for several reasons:</p><p>1. <strong>Reduce Organizational Silos:</strong> Siloed working environments attract numerous engineering problems. By reducing silos, organizations can bring ideas to life more optimally.</p><p>2. <strong>Accept Failure as Normal: </strong>Making mistakes is human, but learning from them is crucial. A blameless culture that performs postmortems of problems enhances the learning curve and encourages teams to take ownership.</p><p>3. <strong>Implement Gradual Change:</strong> Change is essential for growth. The technology landscape is embedded with change management at its core. Software engineering teams live by agile values, are open to changes, and consider rapid development and deployment crucial. Understanding consumer requirements, listening to feedback, and analyzing user data are vital for mutual success. Canary and blue-green deployments exemplify this approach.</p><p>4. <strong>Leverage Tools and Automation:</strong> Introducing automation empowers software engineering teams. This can range from simple tools for capturing screenshots to advanced AI companions for auto-coding. Integrating such systems into workflows boosts company productivity.</p><p>5. <strong>Measure Everything:</strong> While empowering software engineering is crucial, defining success criteria and measuring them is even more critical for business success. Defining KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) enables teams and individuals to enhance their work methods.</p><p>Stay tuned for the next post where we will dive deeper into SLA, SLI, and similar terms.</p><p>Reference:</p><p><a href="https://www.cloudskillsboost.google/course_templates/59">Site Reliability Engineering: Measuring and Managing Reliability | Google Cloud Skills Boost</a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=1c4fa0b85569" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="devops" /><category term="google-cloud-platform" /><category term="site-reliability" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am writing this blog post after taking a course from Google Cloud Boost Skills. It was fascinating to learn about the significance of SRE (Site Reliability Engineering) and DevOps in organizations of any size.Happy Lak is in Richmond Park, watching the deer.Before diving into the importance of SRE and DevOps, let’s understand what DevOps is.Traditionally, developers and operators (the team that deploys and manages systems/applications) functioned in silos, leading to numerous challenges. This separation resulted in increased technical debt, longer time-to-market for solutions, and poor communication and collaboration between teams. Thanks to DevOps practices, teams are now structured in a more integrated manner to address both development and operational needs. This integrated approach reduces time-to-market with calculated risks, introducing terms such as SLA and SLI into the mix.SLA (Service Level Agreement): A commitment between a service provider and a client regarding the expected level of serviceSLI (Service Level Indicator): A measure of the service level provided to the clientA herd of deer is grazing in the park.Connecting five key touchpoints highlights the thin line between SRE and DevOps. Essentially, Class SRE implements DevOps for several reasons:1. Reduce Organizational Silos: Siloed working environments attract numerous engineering problems. By reducing silos, organizations can bring ideas to life more optimally.2. Accept Failure as Normal: Making mistakes is human, but learning from them is crucial. A blameless culture that performs postmortems of problems enhances the learning curve and encourages teams to take ownership.3. Implement Gradual Change: Change is essential for growth. The technology landscape is embedded with change management at its core. Software engineering teams live by agile values, are open to changes, and consider rapid development and deployment crucial. Understanding consumer requirements, listening to feedback, and analyzing user data are vital for mutual success. Canary and blue-green deployments exemplify this approach.4. Leverage Tools and Automation: Introducing automation empowers software engineering teams. This can range from simple tools for capturing screenshots to advanced AI companions for auto-coding. Integrating such systems into workflows boosts company productivity.5. Measure Everything: While empowering software engineering is crucial, defining success criteria and measuring them is even more critical for business success. Defining KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) enables teams and individuals to enhance their work methods.Stay tuned for the next post where we will dive deeper into SLA, SLI, and similar terms.Reference:Site Reliability Engineering: Measuring and Managing Reliability | Google Cloud Skills Boost]]></summary></entry></feed>